... is the principle of that pulsating part, that power within us,
梵天的原理就在那裡，它是我們體內那股(心)跳動力量的原理，
which we have to feel, and which pulsates in everything.
我們必須感受它，它在萬物中跳動。
It happens with Sahaja Yoga, no doubt, that the Kundalini rises,
毫無疑問，霎哈嘉瑜伽會發生，昆達里尼能量會升起，
but that is not the end of it, because human being is the instrument in which this light is manifested.
但這並非終點，因為人類是這道光得以顯現的器皿。
But once it is manifested it is not necessary that it would be all the time burning properly.
但一旦顯現出來，並不代表它會一直明亮燃燒。
There is a possibility, mostly it is a possibility, that the light can go out.
這光有可能熄滅，這種情況非常普遍。
If a wind upside is against it, then it can go out.
如果逆風而行，它就會熄滅。
It can also subside a little bit. It may come out it may flicker, it may dwindle a little bit.
它也可能稍微減弱一些。它可能閃爍，也可能逐漸衰弱。
Because human beings, as they are, they have got into three complications.
因為人類，就他們目前的狀態而言，把自己陷入了三種困境。
As soon as they become human beings these three complications start in them.
一旦他們成為人類，這三種複雜的困境便開始在他們身上顯現。
And because of three, these three complications, one has to know that if you have to get out of that you have to break certain knots.
而由於這三種複雜的困境，人們必須明白，若想從中解脫，就必須解開某些束縛。
They are called as granthis in the Sanskrit language — which are giving you this falsehood — is the vitathat (वितथता)
在梵語中，這些結被稱為「granthis」——正是這些束縛賦予了我們這種虛妄——即“vitathat”（वितथता，虛妄）。
Falsehood that we think that you see, “In this world, after all everything is science,
我們以為你所見的虛妄，是「在這個世界上，畢竟一切都是科學，
and everything is what we see and everything beyond…” And all those sorts of things are really false
一切都是我們所見，以及一切超越的事物……」而這類想法其實都是虛假的
because, unless and until you rise into Reality, you believe in them.
因為，除非你提升到真理的層面，否則你就會相信它們。
After all what is God? And what is all this talk of religion? What is the talk of Christ?
上帝是什麼？所有這些關於宗教的言論又是什麼？關於基督的言論又是什麼？
And what is the talk of all these things?
而這些言論究竟在談論什麼？
So all these problems become sort of identified with you. Absolutely you believe in the falsehood all the time.
因此，所有這些問題似乎都與你息息相關。你始終堅信著虛假的事物。
You are more concerned about the falsehood than about the truth.
你對虛假的關注遠超過對真理的關注。
Even if you are concerned about the truth, when you are born with the seeker’s mind,
即使你關心真理，當你天生就懷有求道者的心態時，
then you try to seek and you try to think of something that is beyond,
然後你試圖尋求，試圖思考某種超越心智的事物，
you try to understand
你試圖理解
that there must be something beyond and something must happen.
必定有某種超越現實的存在，必定有事情會發生。
But still, you see, you are bound
但你看，你仍然被束縛著
by these three complications in life, by which ...
由於生活中的這三種複雜困境，我們...
these three complications we accept the world as it is.
我們接受世界本來的樣子，正是因為這三種複雜情況。
Because we do not know the Reality. The problem is we do not know the Reality.
因為我們不了解實相。問題在於我們不了解實相。
Till we come inside the Reality, we really do not know even what is Reality.
直到我們進入實相之中，我們甚至不知道什麼是實相。
What is the basic substance of our being, how do we live,
我們存在的本質是什麼，我們如何存活，
what is the subtle being, how do we live and what is our aim, what we have to fulfil?
那精微存有是什麼，我們如何生活以及我們活著的的目標是什麼，我們必須完成什麼？
All these questions are very vague in our mind.
所有這些問題在我們腦袋裡都非常模糊。
Then we start seeking here and there, we go round here and there and try to find out.
於是我們開始四處尋求，我們到處奔波，試圖找出答案。
We talk to people, we read books and especially we go to books which are philosophical
我們與人交談，閱讀書籍，特別是去閱讀那些哲學著作，
and try to find out about what must be done about Reality.
試著弄清楚該如何面對實相。
Why are we drawn towards this? Why are we not happy? Why do we feel dissatisfied in life?
為什麼我們被這吸引？為什麼我們不快樂？為什麼我們在生活中感到不滿足？
Why do we all the time hanker after sometimes,
為什麼我們總是渴望某些東西，
something and we do not feel fulfilled within ourselves and, why don’t we understand the meaning of our own being?
有些事讓我們內心感到不滿足，為何我們無法理解自身存在的意義？
Why are we driven like this?
為何我們會如此被驅使？
All these questions come to us…
所有這些問題湧上心頭……
Please come in!
請進！
All these questions come to us and we start seeking about it.
所有這些問題湧向我們，我們便開始尋求解答。
And actually our priorities, before we get into it, are so false
事實上，在我們深入探究之前，我們的優先順序是如此虛假
because we do not know Reality.
因為我們並不了解實相。
So I mean, it’s not your fault, itself,
所以我的意思是，這本身並非你的錯。
if you do not know Reality, and then naturally…For example, somebody, to catch the train itself is very important,
如果你不了解實相，那麼自然……舉例來說，對某人而言，趕上火車本身非常重要，
then to go in time is very important, then to get some money is important
那麼準時前往就非常重要，接著賺取一些錢也很重要，
and to get to a house is important, and then to have some children is important.
擁有一棟房子很重要，然後生兒育女也很重要。
All these things become very much more important than they should be.
所有這些事情變得比它們應有的重要性還要重要得多。
While the main thing, that is to seek within yourself:
當主要的事情，也就是向內尋求時，卻被忽略了：
the point of what are we to seek and what is so important about it,
我們要尋求的重點是什麼，以及它為何如此重要，
that every scripture has talked about this,
每一部經典都談論過這一點，
that you must seek within yourself, you must find out yourself who you are.
你必須向內尋求，你必須自己找出你是誰。
What is the reason? Why all of them have been so much stressing?
原因是什麼？為何所有經書都如此強調？
So until you enter into it you will not know.
所以直到你進入實像，你才會明白。
It is such a vicious circle, because of these three complications I was telling you about.
這是一個惡性循環，因為我剛才提到的這三個困境。
Because if, as it is described, that your Spirit is absolutely a detached personality,
因為如果，真如經書描述的那樣，你的靈是一個完全超脫的人格，
it’s a detached being; it is not contaminated by anything. It is absolutely complete by itself.
它是一個獨立的存在；不受任何事物污染。它自身即是絕對完整的。
It is joy, it is bliss, it is the truth.
它是喜悅，它是極樂，它是真理。
And where are we then?
那麼我們又在哪裡呢？
Why are we in such a mood that we have something very important for us in our life,
為什麼我們會如此執著於生命中那些對我們來說非常重要、
very special for us?
非常特別的事呢？
We think that, “Oh, this must be done. I must get myself insured! I must do these things.”
我們會想：「噢，這件事必須完成。我必須為自己買保險！我必須做這些事。」
Then why, if that Spirit is such a powerful thing, then what is the complication?
那麼，如果靈是如此強大的存在，為什麼會存在這些困境呢？
What are the complications we have and how do we get rid of these complications?
我們面臨的複雜情況是什麼？又該如何擺脫它們？
Through your evolution from the amoeba stage, you can say, even from the absolutely from the, we call it the jad, the dead,
從變形蟲階段，甚至可以說，從絕對的、我們稱之為死寂的狀態，
from the absolutely from the material stage to this state,
從絕對的物質階段到這個狀態，
it has achieved quite a lot of detachment in a way.
你在某種程度上已經達到了相當程度的超脫。
The detachment has come in a way that you understand that you are not the dead;
這種超脫的方式在於，你理解到自己並非那死寂之物；
no, you are not. That much at least everybody knows, that you are not.
不，你不是。至少這一點大家都知道，你不是死寂。
There are so many things you are identified with
你認同於許多事物，
but at least you know that you are not dead.
但至少你知道你並非死寂。
With the growth of materialism and by changing matter and its forms and all that,
隨著物質主義的發展，隨著物質及其形態的改變等等，
then you realise one more thing: that matter doesn’t give us happiness.
然後你意識到另一件事：物質無法帶給我們快樂。
I mean many people through evolution realise it:
我的意思是，許多人透過進化逐漸領悟到：
that matter is not the end of our lives and it is not going to give us happiness.
物質並非人生的終極目標，也無法為我們帶來幸福
Then, in the subtler form, when you evolve even more,
接著，在更精微的層次上，當你進一步進化時，
then you go into the arts and the beauty of the matter:
你會進入藝術領域，領悟物質之美：
then you start seeing little deeper than what the matter means to you,
你會開始看到物質對你而言更深層次的意義，
and you start thinking about its beauty, its forms, its combinations and its harmony.
並且開始思考它的美、它的形態、它的組合與和諧。
So the subtleties about matter develop,
於是關於物質的細微之處便逐漸展現。
up to a point, through your rationality and understanding,
在某種程度上，透過你的理性與理解，
that you realise that this is... this art, also has its finite nature:
你會意識到這門藝術也有其局限性：
I mean how far can you go with it?
我的意思是，你能發展到甚麼地步？
And even if you have art and you become an artist and you are aesthetically very rich…
即使你擁有藝術才華，成為藝術家，並在美學上非常豐富…
there are people who can be called as masters of art and those who are really aesthetically evolved people,
有些人可被稱為藝術大師，而那些真正在美學上有所造詣的人，
but if you go and see their lives you get a shock you realise what kind of artists are these?
但若你去觀察他們的生活，你會感到震驚，你會意識到這些是什麼樣的藝術家？
I mean, they are producing art and beautiful things and nothing goes inside! They are very materialistic,
我的意思是，他們在創作藝術和美好的事物，但內心卻空空如也！他們非常物質主義，
they can be mad people or they can be absolutely obnoxiously boring.
他們可能是瘋狂的人，也可能是極其乏味無趣的人。
So why is it that these artists, you see those who are creating all this,
那麼，為何這些藝術家，你看那些創造出這一切作品的人，
supposed to be something which is joy-giving, are so boring themselves and nothing goes inside them!
這些作品本應帶來快樂，他們自己卻如此乏味，內心空洞無物呢？
And apart from that they are so oppressive, and so much sometimes can be very egoistical
除此之外，他們還如此壓抑，有時可能非常自我中心，
or can be very, very methodical or meticulous and they could be absolutely mathematical about things.
或者可能非常、非常過分的嚴謹細緻，對事物如同數學般精確。
You start understanding that they are not that abstract, as they produce.
你會開始明白，他們本身並不像他們的創作那樣抽象。
You see, they give some ideas, some projections they do, but they may not be so.
你看，它們提供了一些想法、一些設想，但他們本身可能並非如此。
So again you start thinking:
因此，你再次開始思考：
how is it that this matter, which has gone to this subtle state,
為什麼這種已經發展到如此精微的境界，
which is called as art and artists,
被稱為藝術和藝術家的事物，
why is it that this matter has not anything in it to offer us of that eternal value
卻無法提供任何永恆的價值，
or of that nature which is promised to us through our scriptures?
或者說無法提供如同經文中所承諾的那種本質呢？
So some people do at this point,
所以有些人走到這一點，
definitely they step over, I would say, or they just collapse on that point.
肯定會跨越界限，或者說，他們就在那一點上崩潰了。
In the sense then they think, “Oh, then there is nothing like scriptures.
於是他們會想：「哦，那些經文根本什麼都沒有。
It’s all a mess. It’s all wrong. There may not be anything. It’s a tall story told to us.
這一切都亂七八糟。這全都錯了。可能根本不存在。這只是編給我們聽的誇大故事。
And there may not be any truth about it, that there is all pervading power and there is this God
關於無所不在的力量、關於上帝以及你可以與上帝合一的說法，可能根本沒有任何真理。
and you can become one with God. It cannot be true.
這不可能是真的。
After all you can see that there is so much of poverty in this world,
畢竟你可以看到這個世界有如此多的貧困，
there is so much of pain in this world, people are so unhappy, how can there be a God
這個世界有如此多的痛苦，人們如此不快樂，怎麼可能會有神
Who can tolerate all this?”
能夠容忍這一切呢？
I get letters of that kind many a times, you see,
我經常收到這類信件，你知道的，
that, “How people are so unhappy and they are this and that
內容總是「人們為何如此不快樂，他們這樣那樣
and then how can you talk of God?”
那你怎麼還能談論上帝呢？」
So this is the one complication we have
這就是我們面臨的一個困境
and this is the complication comes in, because
而這個困境的根源在於，因為
the Atma, the Spirit, is enveloped by our attention into the matter;
我們的注意力被物質注意包圍，使我們無法專注於靈。
because the matter has risen, our attention has come from matter,
因為物質已經上升，我們的注意力移到了外部，
and it has risen up to a point where there is a knot
並且它已經上升到形成一個結的程度
by which we cannot see the Spirit but we see the matter.
我們無法看見靈，只能看見物質。
This knot, I mean there’s a big controversy about names.
這個結，我的意思是，關於它的名稱一直存在著很大的爭議。
I would not like you to confuse it but we can say like that, this knot is the knot
我不希望你們混淆，但我們可以這樣說，這個結就是那個結
which is the knot between the Spirit and the matter,
也就是靈性與物質之間的結。
which is called as jad-prakruti (जड प्रकृति) in the Sanskrit language.
這在梵語中被稱為 jad-prakruti（無感知、物質性的本質）。
This is the first knot which is a very difficult knot.
這是第一個結，一個非常難解的結。
We think, “This jug is mine.”
我們想著：「這個水壺是我的。」
And we think, “This chair is mine.”
而我們想著：「這張椅子是我的。」
Even if somebody offers you a chair, “Come along sit here!”
就算有人給你一張椅子，「來，坐這裡！」
and the another person is sitting little bit lower, she’ll say, “Oh,
而另一個人坐得稍微低一點，她就會說：「噢，
she has given her a chair which is higher!”
她給了她一張比較高的椅子！」
All kinds of complications human beings have! You know, it’s very delicate they are.
人類就是有各種各樣的複雜心思！你知道嗎，他們的心思非常敏感。
They are so foolishly, sometimes, identified with things, like supposing a person…if you go more and more in the politics now,
他們有時會如此愚蠢地將自己與事物等同起來，就像假設一個人……如果你現在越來越深入政治，
there’s a prime minister and he thinks that someone is sitting on a chair,
就會發現，一個首相，他認為有人坐在某個位置上，
and he thinks that somebody is going to occupy that chair, then you see, all kinds of funny things start in his mind
他認為有人將要佔據那把椅子，然後你看，各種可笑的想法開始在他腦中浮現
and all kinds of complications start. And he thinks that he’ll be dislodged from that chair
各種複雜情況也隨之而來。他認為自己將被從那把椅子上趕下來
by which he’s been a prime minister, so he starts working out his own plans and things.
他因此成為首相，於是開始制定自己的計畫和相關事宜。
I mean the priorities are so much changed!
我的意思是，優先事項已經發生了巨大的變化！
Then you will start, sort of what you call, canvassing for him
然後你將開始，可以說是為他進行拉票活動
and everybody going for an election,
而每個人都為選舉奔波。
and everybody fighting.
而每個人都爭鬥不休。
I mean, the whole world is a madhouse at these things you see:
我的意思是，整個世界在這些事情上就像個瘋人院，你看：
how to achieve that chair, that position, by which he can become the prime minister.
如何取得那個職位、那個位置，藉此他就能成為首相。
And the other one doesn’t come. The other side working it out
而另一個人卻不來。另一邊在盤算著。
and, you see, it is very ‘important’. But what is he putting on the chair, is another dead stuff.
而且，你看，這非常「重要」。但他放在椅子上的，又是另一件死物。
You see one dead is adorned by another dead.
你看，一個死物被另一個死物者裝飾著。
He’s dead as far as so many things are concerned which are thought as the truth,
就許多被視為真理的事物而言，他已經死了，
because he doesn’t know the truth. Now supposing you make somebody as a high priest.
因為他不知道真理。現在假設你讓某人成為大祭司。
Now he is a high priest on a chair.
如今他不過是坐在椅子上的高階祭司。
To me, I see one dead thing sitting on another dead thing, that’s all.
對我而言，我只看到一個死物坐在另一個死物上，僅此而已。
Because the chair doesn’t understand these things, the one who’s put on the chair doesn’t understand anything either,
因為椅子無法理解這些事物，坐在椅子上的人同樣一無所知，
because it hasn’t got the awareness to see what is the truth.
因為他缺乏覺察真相的意識。
So what’s the use of doing such a jocular thing?
那麼，做這樣一件滑稽的事情有什麼用呢？
It’s really a joke, but people are very serious about it indeed. Very serious things,
這確實是個笑話，但人們卻非常認真地對待它。非常認真的事情，
absolutely, they do all kinds of things for these elections. It’s so serious,
絕對的，他們為了這些選舉做了各種各樣的事情。這太認真了，
but if you stand from this angle
但如果你站在這個角度來看
and you should see that you start looking at it and you say, “What’s this? I never expected. What’s all going on?”
而你會發現，當你開始觀察它時，你會說：「這是什麼？我從未料到。這一切是怎麼回事？」
You see, it’s quite silly.
你看，這其實相當愚蠢。
But we have to accept it because we have misidentified
但我們必須接受這一點，因為我們誤認了這「結」（granthi），
through this one granthi, or you can call it this knot
或者你也可以稱之為這個非生命的結
of the jadaprakruthi or what you call as this matter.
所謂的「jadaprakruthi」，或者你所謂的「物質」。
Now for a Sahaja Yogi it is essential to see how far he is identified with his jadaprakruthi.
對於霎哈嘉瑜伽士而言，至關重要的是要看清自己與物質的認同程度。
It’s very important to see how far is he identified with his,
至關重要的是要看清他與自身，
what you call the attachment or the covering of this deadening.
所謂的執著或這種僵化覆蓋物的認同程度有多深。
All that is subconscious is, all what you call conditioning, is done.
所有潛意識的、所有你所謂的制約，都是在過去形成的。
Everything that is dead is dead.
所有死去的事物都是死的。
Whether it is your dead matter or a dead thought, it’s just the same.
無論是你已逝的物質或已逝的念頭，都是一樣的。
And the more you hover on it. You see, there are silly people I have known: I mean they have come to me in their thing.
而你越是沉溺其中，就越是如此。你看，我認識一些愚蠢的人：我是說他們帶著他們的執念來找我。
You see, supposing a wife has died, say about thirty-five years back. Alright?
假設一個妻子已經去世，大概三十五年前。對吧？
So he is here weeping and crying,
所以他在這裡哭泣流淚，
writing poetry about her. She’s dead about twenty-five years back. She might have been reborn as a child somewhere
寫詩歌頌她。她已經去世大約二十五年了。她可能已經在某處轉世為一個孩子
or something like that. He can’t marry her again, nothing of the kind,
或類似的情況。他不可能再娶她，絕對不可能，
but he’s writing poetry about her, crying and weeping. And he expects everybody to weep.
但他卻為她寫詩，哭泣流淚。還期望每個人都跟著哭泣。
There are people, I have seen, they sit down and they just weep about it.
我見過一些人，他們坐下來，就只是為此哭泣。
They just play records and things, melancholy things and just wasting all their precious tears on something that is dead and finished.
他們只是播放唱片之類的東西，那些憂鬱的東西，把寶貴的眼淚浪費在已經逝去、結束的事物上。
Now, there’s no need to weep about it, but they’ll go on like that
現在，根本沒必要為此哭泣，但他們還是會繼續這樣下去。
and they enjoy such a thing very much and they appreciate it very much.
而且他們非常享受這樣的感覺，也非常珍惜。
It’s most surprising! But people go on wasting their energy, they enjoy it in a way,
這真是太令人驚訝了！但人們繼續浪費他們的精力，在某種程度上他們很享受，
the way it is written down, the whole melancholy of singing their
享受著歌詞裡描繪的那種憂傷，
damaged experiences and remembering them in your memory.
享受著歌頌那些傷痛經歷，並將它們銘記於心的感覺。
Whatever was false, actually should become nothing in your mind when you reach Reality.
當你體驗到實相，所有在你的心中虛假的都應歸於虛無。
So the memory in a Sahaja Yogi
因此，對於一位霎哈嘉瑜伽士來說，
is of no value, much value. Because whatever he had, was in a dead condition.
記憶毫無價值，或者說價值甚微。因為那些都處於死寂狀態。
He was not sensitive to All-pervading Power at that time.
那時他對無所不在的力量並不敏感。
He was just dealing with dead stuff, you see.
他只是在處理那些死氣沉沉的事物，你明白的。
And that was what I was surprised when many people told me
而這正是當許多人告訴我時，我感到驚訝的地方
that, “Mother, after becoming a Sahaja Yogi now we can’t read any more melancholy poets.”
「母親，成為霎哈嘉瑜伽士後，我們現在再也讀不下任何憂鬱詩人的作品了。」
I said, “Thank God a lot of time is now saved for meditation!”
我說：「感謝老天，現在有更多時間可以用來靜坐了！」
Otherwise imagine all of them coming with very melancholy faces to me,
否則想像一下，他們全都帶著非常憂傷的面容來找我，
and saying that, “Mother you know, this poet has written…”
並說道：「母親您知道，這位詩人寫了……」
Already there are bombardments of people who read all kinds of books, that,
已經有許多人讀了各種書籍後前來質問，
“Why such a person should write like that? And why such a person should write like that?”
「為什麼這樣的人會寫出這樣的東西？又為什麼那樣的人會寫出那樣的東西？」
In the same way they would say, why is such a person like Lord Byron?
同樣地，他們會說，像拜倫勳爵這樣的詩人究竟是怎麼回事？
I don’t even see his face you see,
我甚至沒見過他的臉，你知道嗎，
when we pass that way! I say he’s really melancholia personified!
當我們經過那條路時！我說他簡直就是憂鬱的化身！
And he made everybody miserable himself! What was he crying about? I mean if you see his life: whom did he make happy?
而且他讓每個人都痛苦不堪！他到底在哭什麼？我是說，如果你看看他的一生：他讓誰快樂過？
He made everyone happy, and was crying all the time and still making everybody unhappy?
他讓每個快樂的人，卻又總是哭泣，最後還是讓每個人都不快樂？
So this kind of a person is there! All this is dead and takes you towards the dead.
這樣的人就存在於世上！死物最終只會將你引向死亡。
So dead and dead things can never give you happiness.
因此，無生命和死物永遠無法給你帶來快樂。
On the contrary it gives you habits, they give you habits.
相反地，它會讓你養成習慣，習慣會潛移默化地影響你。
And these habits come to you like, say, you are habituated to sit on the chair, you cannot sit on the ground.
而這些習慣會影響你，比如說，你習慣坐在椅子上，你就無法坐在地上。
Now if I tell the Sahaja Yogis they must learn to sit on the ground
現在如果我告訴霎哈嘉瑜伽士，他們必須學會坐在地上
they will immediately start that, “We must sit on the ground!” That’s not the point!
他們會立刻開始說：「我們必須坐在地上！」這不是重點！
What I am saying the habit the chair has given should be got rid of.
我所說的是，你應該擺脫椅子帶來的習慣。
But for that you don’t waste your energies, for heaven’s sake!
但千萬不要為此浪費精力！
Because if I say that then you shouldn’t try wasting your energy in getting rid of the habits that were there.
因為如果我這麼說，你就不該試圖浪費精力去擺脫那些已有的習慣。
On the contrary if you put your attention to your Spirit, to what you have achieved,
相反地，如果你將注意力放在你的靈上，放在你已達成的成就上，
to where you are, gradually you’ll find your habits will drop out like that.
放在你所在的位置上，你就會逐漸發現你的習慣會自然而然地消失。
You have known that. We have had alcoholics with us here; terrible alcoholics who could not give up alcohol,
你們都知道。我們這裡曾有酗酒者；非常嚴重的酒鬼，他們戒不了酒，
and they have given up.
但來到這他們都戒掉了。
We have had people who have taken drugs; they have given up without any difficulties.
我們曾有吸毒的人；他們毫無困難地戒除了。
Cigarettes they have given up. I mean there are also some higher vices and bigger vices also people have given up.
菸癮他們也戒掉了。我的意思是，還有一些更高層次的惡習和更嚴重的惡習，人們也同樣戒除了。
And some vices which one cannot mention, people have given up.
而有些難以啟齒的惡習，人們也已經戒除了。
So this happens when your attention goes to your Spirit.
所以當你的注意力轉向你的靈時，這種情況就會發生。
And this is a very big detachment that comes to you
這是一種非常巨大的超脫感降臨於你
through your ascent, into that realm where you feel the All-pervading.
透過你的提升，進入那個你能感受到無所不在的境界。
Means automatically your detachment works.
意味著你的超脫自動運作。
Means your attention has felt, definitely, that oneness with Reality. Otherwise why are you getting detached?
意味著你的注意力確實感受到了與實相的一體性。否則你為何會變得超然？
And spontaneously it happens. Suddenly you’ve matured so much. Sahaja Yogis matured so fast.
這是自然而然地發生的。突然間你變得如此成熟。霎哈嘉瑜伽士成熟得如此迅速。
I mean it’s a jet-like maturity, I think. Because when they rise nobody understands, you see.
我認為這是一種噴射機般的成熟速度。因為當他們提升時，沒有人能理解，你看。
Whenever they say something people say, “What are you talking about?”
每當他們說些什麼，人們總是回應：「你到底在說什麼啊？」
Because they are at such a different level that others just don’t understand what they are talking about,
因為他們的層次實在相差太遠，其他人根本無法理解他們在談論什麼，
and they find it very difficult to understand.
而且理解起來也極其困難。
Easiest thing, whatever they talk, the others say, “What, what are you saying about, we don’t follow?”
最簡單的情況就是，不管他們談論什麼，其他人總是說：「什麼？你到底在說什麼？我們聽不懂。」
So the attention when it enters into that, your habits drop out.
所以當注意力進入那個狀態時，你的習慣就會消失。
But for that it is essential that your attention should be on your Spirit.
但要做到這一點，關鍵在於你的注意力必須專注於你的靈。
Now what is the beauty of Spirit for a Sahaja Yogi? What does he get out of the Spirit? What is the manifestation of Spirit is?
那麼，對於霎哈嘉瑜伽士來說，靈的美妙之處是什麼？他能從靈中得到什麼？靈的顯現又是什麼？
That when his attention is absolutely one with the Atman, with the Spirit,
那就是當他的注意力完全與靈魂、與靈合而為一時。
then there is a manifestation of vibrations. You start getting cool breeze in your hands.
接著，生命能量便顯現出來。你的雙手開始感受到涼爽的微風。
Now these vibrations are there from the very beginning of the matter, up to the vibrations where you come up to a human level.
這些生命能量從物質的最初階段就已存在，一直延伸到人類層次。
So you can call them, these are like, electromagnetic vibrations.
因此，你可以稱它們為類似電磁振動的東西。
But when they go on improving. You see, in the beginning, they just look like electromagnetic,
但當它們持續改善時，你會發現，起初它們看起來就像是電磁振動，
then they look like more. There is emotions in it, you see.
後來它們展現出更多內涵，你看，這裡面有情感。
Then you go little ahead, then you find that these vibrations also act.
然後你再深入一些，你會發現這些生命能量也會行動，
These vibrations also think, they also report.
也會思考，它們也會傳遞訊息。
So, you see, gradually you will find that with the growth of human being,
所以你看，漸漸地你會發現，隨著人類的成長，
as a human being from matter,
作為一個來自物質的人類，
these vibrations have also manifested into different categories.
這些生命能量也顯現為不同的類別。
To begin with, these vibrations are only electromagnetic, you can say, in the matter.
首先，這些生命能量在物質層面上只是電磁振波。
Say if you have Sulphur Dioxide as a molecule you will find sulphur and dioxide both are vibrating all the time like that.
比方說，如果你有一個二氧化硫分子，你會發現硫和二氧化物兩者都一直在那樣振動。
But when it goes on manifesting more and more. That’s the basics,
但當它持續展現得越來越多時，那就是基礎，
then gradually the manifestation of these higher things can be perceived through our understanding of Sahaja Yoga.
然後透過我們對霎哈嘉瑜伽的理解，這些更高層次事物的展現便能逐漸被感知。
But for a normal person it is only electromagnetic.
但對一般人來說，它僅僅是電磁性的。
Now supposing a matter, which is, say, just a matter, say a dead matter, it is.
現在假設有一種物質，它僅僅是物質，比如說一種無生命的物質，它就是如此。
Now it is not aware that it has got vibrations to begin with.
它現在並未意識到自己一開始就擁有生命能量。
It is not aware.
它並未察覺。
It doesn’t even think about it. I mean, it has no awareness at all of any kind, it’s just dead.
它甚至沒有思考過這件事。我的意思是，它對任何事物都毫無感知，它就是無生命的。
So, but there are vibrations, there are electromagnetic vibrations, but it is not aware.
所以，生命能量確實存在，存在電磁振波，但它卻沒有意識到。
Now supposing such a dead matter, if you tell that dead matter that you have vibrations it will say, “What are you talking about?
現在假設有這樣一種無生命的物質，如果你告訴它你擁有生命能量，它會說：「你在說什麼？
I have never felt!” But somebody else can feel it,
我從未感受過！」但其他人卻能感受到，
that there are electromagnetic vibrations. In the same way every human being has got these vibrations within him in the Spirit.
那就是電磁振動的存在。同樣地，每個人內在的靈都存在著這些生命能量。
But they are only manifested when he gets Realisation.
但它們只有在獲得自覺時，才會顯現出來。
So, the second category of the same thing, the same vibrations, start expressing higher and higher qualities about it.
因此，第二類的相同事物、相同的生命能量，開始展現出越來越高層次的特性。
Like from one seed a tree grows and the flowers come out, and they give fragrance: like that the growth is more and more.
就像從一顆種子長成大樹，花朵綻放並散發香氣：這樣的成長是持續不斷的。
But the basic is electromagnetic vibrations that you can feel it everywhere
但根本在於電磁振波，你可以在任何地方感受到它
in the matter with your naked eyes, a human being can see it.
在物質世界中，人類用肉眼就能看見。
Now see your own growth. Have you recognised it that animals don’t know that there are electromagnetic vibrations,
現在看看你自己的成長。你是否已經認識到，動物並不知道有電磁振波的存在，
but human beings have?
但人類卻知道？
But a Sahaja Yogi knows that there are not only electromagnetic but there are all kinds of manifestations of these vibrations.
然而，一位霎哈嘉瑜伽士明白，不僅有電磁振動，還有各種這些生命能量的顯現形式。
So electromagnetic are important at a point and then other vibrations are even much more important.
因此，電磁振波在某個階段是重要的，但其他生命能量甚至更為重要。
So all these vibrations are coming, combined together, absolutely completely, in a human being, which they manifest gradually.
因此，所有這些生命能量匯聚而來，在人體內完全融合，並逐漸顯現出來。
And they act according to the need of the time.
它們會根據時代的需求而行動。
So much so that in these vibrations there is somebody who thinks,
以至於在這些生命能量中，存在著某個思考者，
the vibrations who think,
那些思考著的生命能量。
the vibrations who cooperate,
生命能量之間相互協作，
who cure,
它們治癒疾病，
who relay things, who report things.
傳遞訊息，報告事物。
All that you think in the human awareness that you are doing it, like telecommunications, you have got big telecommunications:
所有你在人類意識中認為自己正在做的事，比如電信，你已經擁有了龐大的電信系統：
sitting down here you can say show some things that are happening in India or something like that.
坐在這裡，你可以說展示一些在印度發生的事情或類似的事情。
In the same way these vibrations can report things to you. The complete telecommunication is built in these vibrations!
同樣地，這些生命能量，可以向你報告事情。完整的電信系統就蘊藏在這些生命能量中！
Then you can cure people sitting down here.
然後，你可以坐在這裡治癒人們。
You can raise their kundalinis sitting down here.
你可以坐在這裡提升他們的昆達里尼。
You can work out on people sitting down here. All these far fetched things are possible.
你可以坐在這裡為他人進行療癒。所有這些看似不可思議的事情都是可能的。
Those who have been Sahaja Yogis have realised it and seen it and worked it out.
那些已經成為霎哈嘉瑜伽士的人已經意識到、見證並實踐了這一點。
And it’s most surprising. Now we have a lady here sitting down: her husband used to drink a lot, everybody knows the story very well.
這真是最令人驚訝的。現在我們這裡有一位女士坐著：她的丈夫過去常常大量飲酒，每個人都非常清楚這個故事。
And we just sent some vibrations and he’s stopped his drinking. He stopped his drinking.
我們只是發送了一些生命能量，他就停止了飲酒。他就戒酒了。
And just to convince that through vibrations it was done I used something which is very simple, is a lime, is a living lime.
為了證明這是透過生命能量實現的，我用了一個非常簡單的東西——一個青檸，一個活生生的青檸。
And we put our vibrations into that
我們將我們的生命能量注入其中
and we put them near the head of the patient
並將它們放置在患者的頭部附近
and they suck the negativity of the person and the person gives up drinking.
青檸吸收了病人的負能量，病人就戒酒了。
You have seen one boy who used to come here, a little boy,
你見過一個以前常來這裡的小男孩，
who would run all over the places and would not sit down even for a minute.
他總是到處亂跑，連一分鐘都坐不住。
He was possessed, he was horrid.
他被附身了，真是可怕。
And now he’s a sensible boy. He’s started going to school.
現在他變成了一個懂事的孩子，已經開始上學了。
He never used to utter even a word, now he’s started speaking.
他以前從不開口說一句話，現在卻開始說話了。
So all these things happened with the lime?
所以這些事都和那顆青檸有關嗎？
Now he said, “How is it, Mother, a lime is such a thing now?”
現在他說：「母親，青檸怎麼會有這種作用呢？」
For a very, sort of, up to date person, it is a little funny to see limes being used for vibrations!
對於一個非常、可以說是，現代時髦的人來說，看到青檸被用來做生命能量療法，實在有點滑稽！
But they are actually ultra-modern things you know, they are ultra-modern.
但你知道，它們其實是超現代的東西，它們是超現代的。
I am not talking of only modern
我不僅僅是在談論現代
but ultra-modern things are limes; are the very ultra-modern things.
而是超現代的東西就是青檸；正是那些極度超現代的東西。
Because you vibrate the ultra-modern limes
因為你可以用自己的生命能量來啟發這些非常現代的青檸，
by your vibrations, and you put them under the pillow.
將它們放在枕頭下。
Now these limes have a speciality.
現在這些青檸有一個特性。
And this have been found out by many people long time back:
而這在很久以前就被許多人發現了：
that they have a speciality to suck in the vibrations and contain the vibrations
它們有一個特性，它們有一種吸收生命能量並儲存生命能量的特殊能力，
or to, not only electromagnetic,
或者說，不僅僅是電磁波，
but quite a lot of vibrations can be in it, because they are living and they have a coefficience.
還有相當多的生命能量能夠存在其中，因為它們是活生生的，並且擁有一種係數。
They have a kind of coefficience
它們擁有一種係數，
by which they suck in these vibrations in them,
藉此將這些生命能量吸入自身之中。
and then they relay, they throw these vibrations whenever it is necessary.
然後在需要的時候傳遞、釋放這些生命能量。
It's not the limes that do it
並非檸檬本身所為
but the vibrations who are contained in them that they do. How? I will tell you.
而是檸檬中所蘊含的生命能量在起作用。如何做到？我來告訴你。
You can think of a battery being created.
你可以想像一個電池的製造過程。
You create a battery. Now the battery cannot do anything
你創造了一個電池。現在這個電池無法做任何事情
but if you take the battery near some points then it starts working,
但如果你把電池靠近某些點，它就會開始運作，
because it is inside it. In the same way we really make it into a battery.
因為能量就在裡面。同樣地，我們實際上是在把它變成一個電池。
When they are near the heads of the people, these limes, you see.
當這些青檸靠近人們的頭部時，
They are doing nothing, but these vibrations come out and they start working it out.
他們什麼都沒做，但這些生命能量就出現了，然後他們開始著手處理。
It’s a perfect team. They do it, they know, they are perfect.
這是一個完美的團隊。它們自己就能做到，他們知道，他們是完美的。
You don’t have to tell them. They understand much more than you do.
你不需要告訴他們。他們的理解遠比你多。
They are controlled much better
他們被控制得更好
and they know how to find the ways to extract the negativity,
他們懂得如何找到方法來提取負面能量，
which sounds very funny to other people.
這在其他人看來可能很滑稽。
That’s why I tell all the Sahaja Yogis, “Don’t give out all the secrets just now.
這就是為什麼我告訴所有霎哈嘉瑜伽士：「現在不要把所有秘密都說出來。
Let them come in slowly. Let them settle down, let them get vibrations and then we’ll talk.”
讓他們慢慢進來。讓他們安定下來，讓他們感受到生命能量，然後我們再談。」
Because I have seen if you not only talk,
因為我見過，如果你不只是說說而已，
but if they see that I am handling some limes, some people run away,
但如果他們看到我在處理一些青檸，有些人就會跑開，
thinking that it’s all hocus-pocus, you see.
認為這全是騙人的把戲，你懂的。
They don’t want to believe in it. Really it is a fact!
他們不願意相信。但這真的是事實！
Because people believe in some sort of a funny thing.
因為人們總是相信一些稀奇古怪的東西。
Supposing I have big circus
假設我有一個大型馬戲團
and all those things that the people do,
表演各種滑稽的節目，
I don’t know what all they do, but some sort of a funny thing, you see, they like it.
我不知道他們具體做些什麼，但就是某種稀奇古怪的事物，你看，他們喜歡它。
For example, if I make you all jump on your heads
舉例來說，如果我讓你們全都倒立
and shout loudly and make some nuisance out of it
並大聲喊叫，製造一些騷動
there will be thousands coming to this group I can assure you.
我可以向你保證，將有成千上萬的人參加這個活動。
But, if you see, you are really knowing about Reality
但你看，你其實正在了解實相
and if you are handling the vibrations within you people won’t come.
如果你能駕馭你內在的生命能量，，人們就不會來。
And that’s why many people go to that. Why?
這就是為什麼很多人會去參加那些活動。為什麼呢？
Because the same, the complication, the complication is still at work you see.
因為同樣的，那些困境仍然存在。那種複雜性仍在運作，你明白嗎。
So to please them you have to use the complications.
所以為了取悅他們，你必須利用這些困境。
And those who do not want
而那些不願
people to know Reality or those who I would say do not know Reality,
讓人們認識實相，或者我該說，那些根本不了解實相的人，
those people who just want to make use of all this, they use this complication.
那些只想利用這一切的人，他們利用了這種複雜性。
So they try on human beings and that’s how they trap the disciples and that’s how they manage thousands of people
他們以人為目標，以此誘騙信徒，以此控製成千上萬的人，
bringing money and giving them honour
讓他們帶錢、名氣等等，
and all those things which are useless for a person who has known Reality.
以及所有那些對已一個真正了解實相的人毫無用處的事物。
For him money makes no difference. I mean he understands the joke of the money
對他而言，金錢毫無價值。我的意思是，他理解金錢的虛妄
and he understands the joke of everything else.
並且他也理解其他一切事物的虛妄之處。
But those who want to use this complication...
但那些想要利用這個複雜性的人...
So this one is described, I mean... I will use the name that was used by Shankaracharya,
所以這個被描述為，我的意思是...我會使用商羯羅所用的名字來形容這種困境。
because you see everybody is not a realised-soul and of a great authority,
因為你看，並非每個人都是開悟的靈或有極大的權威，
but we have to have some people as authority. So Shankaracharya has called this as Brahmagranthi he calls it Brahmagranthi.
但我們必須有一些人作為權威。所以商羯羅大師稱之為梵天之結，他稱之為梵結（Brahmagranthi）。
Brahmagranthi he says, because the Brahma is the vibrating force, Brahma is Om.
他說這是梵天結，因為梵天是生命能量的力量，梵即是唵。
That is the vibrating force,
那就是生命能量的力量，
because it’s the vibrations, that’s why he calls it as the Brahmagranthi.
正因為它是生命能量，所以他稱之為梵天結。
Now the second one is the one by which we think that we can do something.
現在第二個是我們認為自己能有所作為的那個。
Now this one is the superego one, the first one I told you about: creates the superego, this granthi, the knot, you see..
現在這是超我，我先前告訴你的第一個結：它創造了超我，這個結，你瞧。
How do you have a knot?
你怎麼會有個結呢？結是怎麼形成的呢？
I’ll give you an example of a balloon, say, for example, a balloon.
我給你舉個氣球的例子，比方說，一個氣球。
Now a balloon has lots of air in it,
現在氣球裡面充滿了空氣，
but it will all pass out, it won’t be there, if there is no knot there, you see.
但如果沒有打結，空氣就會漏光，氣球就不存在了。你明白的。
But if there is a knot you can hold the balloon all right.
但如果有一個結，你就能穩穩地抓住氣球。
And this is the balloon we have in our head which we call as superego,
而這就是我們腦中的氣球，我們稱之為超我，
which we can see here clearly. Can you show them?
在這裡我們可以清楚地看到。你能展示給他們看嗎？
The black one, you know. The black, real one, is this one:
黑色的那個，你知道的。黑色的，真正的黑色，是這個：
is the superego by which you get possessed, and you get all mad and you do all kinds of things.
是那個讓你著魔的超我，讓你變得瘋狂，做出各種各樣的事情。
This is the Brahmagranthi. This knot is there.
這就是梵天結。這個結就在那裡。
And this knot, you see, first starts at the Mooladhara. Now...
而這個結，你看，首先從根輪開始。現在...
It starts from there. The knot starts from there, can you imagine! It starts from there!
它從那裡開始。那個結從那裡開始，你能想像嗎！它從那裡開始！
Because this one is made of prithvi-tattwa, is made of the earth element,
因為這個是由土元素構成的，是由土元素構成，
so from the very beginning from the earth element itself, the knot starts.
所以從一開始，從土元素本身，那個結就開始了。
But as there is a knot: you see, when you make a knot always there is an unwinding, always.
但既然有個結：你看，當你打結時，總會有解開的時候，總是如此。
You come by a staircase you always can go down it.
你遇到一段樓梯，總是可以往下走。
Is there a staircase by which you cannot go down but only come up?
是否有一段樓梯只能往上走，卻不能往下走？
In the same way, if you have made a knot, there must be a way of going out of the knot.
同樣地，如果你打了一個結，必定有方法可以解開這個結。
So the going out of the knot is worked out through Sahaj Yoga.
因此，解開結的方法是透過霎哈嘉瑜伽來完成的。
That also is done through vibrations.
這同樣是透過生命能量來完成的。
That the first, this knot, has to be released.
首先，這個結必須被解開。
Once this knot is released then only the Kundalini starts.
一旦這個結被解開，昆達里尼才會開始啟動。
This is the first knot. This is much more important.
這是第一個結。這一點至關重要。
So this first knot is very strong among Indians and is not so strong with you people.
所以這第一個結在印度人中非常牢固，在你們身上卻沒那麼強烈。
Though in a way you have done one great harm
雖然在某種程度上你們造成了一個巨大的傷害
but this one is not so strong in you people, at least those who are seekers.
但這個結在你們身上並不那麼牢固，至少對那些尋求真理的人身上來說是如此。
You are not so materialistic:
你們沒那麼物質主義：
in the sense at least in your rationality,
至少在你的理性層面上，
I think you are.
我認為你是。
But I would say that you are not so much worried about your food
但我會說，你並不像印度人那樣
and things like that, so much as the Indians are.
過於擔憂食物之類的事情。
I mean they can’t help it.
我的意思是他們也無可奈何。
They have to worry about their food and all these things.
他們必須為食物和這些事情操心。
Of course you get your doles, you are not so much worried about these things.
當然你有救濟金可領，就不必那麼擔心這些事了。
But there is also another problem that comes up with all this affluence, that in a very subtle way,
但伴隨這一切富裕而來的還有另一個問題，它以一種非常精微、非常隱晦的方式，
very subtle way, you are materialistic, you are.
你們骨子裡其實挺物質的。
Because if you see, if there is 1p increase, you see, the whole thing topples down,
因為你看，只要價格上漲 1 便士，整個體係就會崩盤，
which won’t happen in India.
但在印度就不會發生這種事。
Even if there is a 3p increase nobody would bother,
就算漲了 3 便士，也沒人會在意。
because they’ll say, “Alright, we’ll not eat that, we’ll have another one!”
因為他們會說：「好吧，我們不吃那個，我們吃別的就好！」
You see, because they are so much used to a kind of calamity
你看，因為他們已經太習慣某種災難
all the time falling on them. “All right if we can’t get bread, we’ll make something else, all right.”
總是降臨在他們身上。「好吧，如果我們得不到麵包，我們就做點別的，沒關係。」
So like that they are not so much disturbed as you people are.
所以他們不像你們這些人那樣焦慮，受到那麼大的困擾。
Because you become over-sensitive, even to your materialism you are very sensitive
因為你變得過度敏感，甚至對你的物質主義也極度敏感
and your materialism starts becoming so funny that it amounts to fuss,
而你的物質主義開始變得如此可笑，簡直到了小題大做的地步，
and it’s fussy. It’s a fussy materialism which is such a headache, I tell you,
而且還很矯情。這是一種吹毛求疵的物質主義，真是令人頭痛，我告訴你，
that I mean even what people are wearing and how they are dressed…
我的意思是，甚至連人們穿什麼、怎麼打扮都要管…
Now supposing you are wearing a suit,
現在假設你穿著一套西裝，
then they say it’s not good because, “He’s a very suity fellow. He’s a suity fellow.”
那麼他們會說這不好，因為「他是個很西裝的人。太正式了。」
Now if he is not wearing a suit,
現在如果他沒穿西裝，
then, “He’s very casual,” you see. Sort of everything has a name something like that.
那麼，「他非常休閒」，你瞧。好像什麼都要貼個標籤似的。這類事情總有個說法，大概就是這樣。
And everything can be discarded under some banner or something.
而且什麼都可以被歸類到某個標籤下。
I mean who has got time to think about who is wearing what,
我是說，誰有時間去想誰穿了什麼，
who’s a suity or a booty or whatever it is?
誰是西裝革履的紳士，誰是穿著暴露的花花公子，或其他什麼？
You see! But these things make you sort of brand a person,
你看吧！但這些事情會讓你給人貼上某種標籤。
that a person, his house is like this, then he must be like this. It is not so. It is not.
一個人，他的房子是這樣，那麼他一定就是這樣。事實並非如此。根本不是。
You see, here the knot is so subtle in the sense
你看，這裡的結是如此精微，在於
that rationality, gives you this sense,
理性，給了你這種感覺，
that by judging it, that by that you judge a person, you judge a person, by his appearance.
藉由評斷它，藉此評斷一個人，你評斷一個人，是根據他的外表。
Say supposing I wear a horn, you can say,
假設我戴著一頂角帽，你可以這麼說，
and I try to do some tricks, you see,
而我試著表演一些把戲，你看，
some jugglery for you. Supposing I show you some money,
為你變些戲法。假設我展示一些錢幣給你，
taking out some sort of... some sort of a ring or something like that.
再拿出某種……某種戒指或類似的東西。
It may really make you feel that, “There must be something about it!”
這或許真的會讓你覺得，「這其中必定有什麼奧妙！」
Or even higher than that if I say that, “All right, you can have your sex habits as you like.
或者，如果我說：「好吧，你可以隨心所欲地追求你的性習慣。
You can have ten women around you. It doesn’t matter and you can meet God.”
你可以有十個女人圍繞在你身邊。這沒關係，你依然可以遇見上帝。」
And if you see someone like that you can call him a sadhu, you can. I mean, it is such a big myth,
如果你看到這樣的人，你可以稱他為聖人，真的可以。我的意思是，這是一個多麼大的迷思啊，
it is such a big falsehood.
這簡直是天大的謊言。
It is absolutely nothing but, I would say, complete darkness, it is.
要我說，它除了黑暗之外，什麼都不是。
But people will accept it, because it will sound
但人們會接受它，因為聽起來
very fantastic to them, because it will support that materialism
對他們來說非常奇幻，因為它迎合了這類人內心深處的物質主義。
that exists within a person like that. You see?
因為它迎合了這類人內心深處的物質主義。明白嗎？
In India, say there is a saint and who says that by sex you will go to God.
在印度，假設有一位聖人說，透過性，你將能接近神。
Immediately people will jump on him, because
人們立刻就會對他群起攻之，因為
you see, we are so much endowed with sex energy,
你看，我們被賦予了如此多的性能量，
hoping we are going to get these higher things.
希望我們能獲得這些更高層次的事物。
All these things happen in a society which is supposed to be absolutely non-materialistic.
所有這些事情都發生在一個理應完全非物質主義的社會中。
So this materialism works out
因此這種物質主義得以運作
and this granthi, what I call the Brahmagranthi,
而這個結，我稱之為梵結，
is the involvement, or you can say the falsehood, the falsehood, of matter.
是物質的涉入，或者你可以說是虛假，物質的虛假。
The falsehood of matter works through this and one goes on believing it and believing it.
物質的虛假透過這個運作，而人們持續相信它、相信它。
So the second thing starts with it that people say, “Let us give up this falsehood.”
於是第二件事隨之而來，人們說：「讓我們放棄這種虛假吧。」
And they start all kinds of another artificial methods.
然後他們開始各種其他的人為方法。
After all, materialism gives you artificiality,
畢竟，唯物主義本身就帶有虛假性
in the sense that when your attention is involved into things which are not real,
意思是當你的注意力被捲入那些不真實的事物中，
which is not Reality, then naturally it is an artificial stuff.  Everything becomes artificial.
那些並非真實的事物，自然而然地，一切都變得虛假了。
And when the artificiality becomes too much,
而當虛假變得過多時，
then what happens, artificially you try to give it up.
那麼接下來會發生什麼呢？你人為刻意地試圖放棄它。
This is the second side of it.
這就是問題的另一面。
The second side of it is artificially you think, “We should give it up.”
問題的另一面是，你會刻意地認為：「我們應該放棄它。」
For example, you will say, “All right, from today I am going to wear a dress like an ascetic!
例如，你會說：「好吧，從今天起，我要像苦行僧一樣穿著長袍！」
We had some people who said that, “We cannot give up these dresses of primitive people.” I said, “But why?”
有些人曾說：「我們不能放棄這些原始人的服飾。」我問：「但為什麼呢？」
“Because we want to become primitive!” Now you cannot become primitive.
「因為我們想變得原始！」但現在你無法變得原始。
It’s a fact! You must accept it. Yes, all right, dress up as you like, it’s nothing important.
這是事實！你必須接受它。是的，好吧，隨你喜歡怎麼打扮，這並不重要。
You see, you dress up like anything but you don’t think by dressing up anything you are going to become anything.
你看，你可以打扮成任何樣子，但別以為靠著打扮就能變成什麼。
Nothing! It is not important at all.
什麼也不會！這根本不重要。
Whatever way you may dress up, whatever things you may dress up, whatever you may do,
無論你如何裝扮，無論你裝扮什麼，無論你做什麼，
has no bearing on your inner yoga.
都與你的內在連結無關。
Inner yoga works out by itself,
內在連結會自然而然地運作。
it works out through chakras,
它透過輪穴運作，
it goes inside, it’s a subtle thing which is a detached thing from, how you dress:
它進入內在，這是一種細微的體驗，與你的穿著方式無關：
how you walk, how you talk is not the point.
你如何行走、如何說話並非重點。
Once this yoga works out then of course, the things change outside;
一旦這種連結發揮作用，外在的事物自然會改變；
because your faces glow,
因為你的面容煥發光彩，
you become magnetic,
你變得充滿吸引力，
you talk in a way which is authoritative,
你的言談充滿權威感，
you start curing people,
你開始治癒他人，
you start doing many things which shows that you are a different person: that’s a very different thing altogether.
你開始做許多事情來顯示自己是個不同的人：這完全是另一回事。
But normally by doing it outside, artificially doing something:
但通常情況下，透過外在的方式，人為刻意地去做某些事情：
you see this is another kind of a granthi, you can call a knot.
你看，這是另一種束縛，你可以稱之為結。
And this knot starts by identifying yourself,
而這個結始於你對自我的認同，
by thinking that if you do something then you are going to achieve it.
以為只要做了某件事就能達成目標。
By... by sort of doing some sort of an effort
透過...透過某種努力
or by doing some sort of a penance
或是透過某種苦行
or sort of standing on your heads or so called Hatha Yoga,
或是某種倒立或所謂的哈達瑜伽
or all these things that people do in the name of God also.
因為人們以神之名所做的這一切也是如此。
All these things you think you are going to achieve, is another falsehood.
你以為自己能夠達成的所有目標，這些又是另一種虛妄。
Because with this falsehood that knot becomes stronger and stronger.
因為隨著這種虛妄，那個結變得越來越牢固。
Doing anything, is what you call the Rajoguna, is the Rajoguna, is the Right side action.
做任何事情，就是你所謂的拉賈古納，就是右脈，就是右脈的行動。
The Left Side action just now I described to you, which starts from the Mooladhara.
我剛才向你們描述的左脈行動，是從根輪開始的。
And the Right Side action, which is the Rajoguna which is within you,
而右脈的行動，是存在於你內在的右脈，
which is the activity within us,
也就是我們內在的活動，
by which we do something, we want to do something;
透過它我們會去做某些事，我們想要去做某些事；
which is done through our ahamkara, is through our ego which is there.
這一切是透過我們的自我，也就是我們存在的自我來完成的。
And all this also, doesn’t lead you anywhere,
而這一切，也無法引領你到達任何地方，
because whatever you do, you do not do any living work, you do all dead.
因為無論你做什麼，你所做的都不是”活”的，而是無生命的。
Supposing you have made this chair: what have you done?
假設你製作了這把椅子：你做了什麼呢？
You have just changed a tree into a dead stuff and then made a chair, that’s all .
你只是把一棵樹變成死物，然後做成一把椅子，如此而已。
dead into dead. You have created all this, it’s all dead and that is all dead
死物變成死物。你創造了這一切，全都是死物，而這一切也都是死物。
Any living work human beings have done? Nothing.
人類做過任何有生命的工作嗎？沒有。
And, if evolution is a living process you are doing all living: you have to do something living.
而且，如果演化是一個有生命的過程，那麼你就是在做一個生命活動：你必須做些有生命(活)的事。
On the contrary if you are doing something dead and believing that you are doing something living, then it’s even a greater falsehood.
相反地，如果你做的是死的，卻誤以為自己在做有生命的事情，那便是更大的虛妄。
But if you realise that we are doing nothing, that is living,
但若你意識到我們什麼也沒做，那才是活著的狀態，
for that something has to happen,
因為某些事必須發生，
that we should be endowed with that Power by which we do living things:
我們應當被賦予那種力量，藉此我們才能做出充滿生命力的事。
if this is accepted then the thing works out, otherwise not.
如果這被接受，事情就能解決，否則就行不通。
If people think, “No, I am the prime minister!”
如果人們想：「不，我是總理！」
say, “I am the king!” “I am the XYZ!”
說：「我是國王！」「我是某某某！」
you may be anything, still for God you are a dead person.
你可能成為任何身分，但在神眼中你仍是個死物。
It matters nothing to God.
這對上帝來說無關緊要。
You might be an engineer, all right you are, you arrange, say for example
你可能是一位工程師，沒錯，你就是，你安排，比方說
you arrange a machinery or something to work out.
你安排一台機器或什麼東西來運作。
Even if you go to Moon, what is it?
即使你去了月球，你得到了什麼？
Dead going to the dead and coming back dead! What have you achieved?
無生命物去往無生命之地，然後無生命物回來！你取得了什麼成就？
Going to the Moon, what did you get?
登上月球，你們得到了什麼？
Those stones, things, and what are you going to put them in, on your heads?
那些石頭、物品，你打算怎麼用？頂在頭上嗎？
What living thing have you done out if it? Just think it over.
你用它們創造了什麼有生命的東西？好好想一想吧。
What efforts! What mind!
多麼巨大的努力！多麼奇特的思維！
Then coming to religion, also we behave in the same manner.
接著談到宗教，我們的行為方式也如出一轍。
We think if we go to church, now for example
我們認為如果去教堂，現在舉例來說
some people believe in it. Of course, I mean some of you are sensible enough to understand
有些人相信它。當然，我的意思是你們當中有些人足夠明智，能夠理解
that by going to church and listening to a priest you are not going to achieve anything.
明白去教會聽牧師講道並不能帶來任何益處。
Is a sensible thing, that way.
這樣看來，這是明智的。
But even by going to temples, you are not going to achieve it, take it from me.
但即使去寺廟參拜，也得不到任何益處，相信我。
Going to any lectures, you are not going to achieve it.
參加任何講座，你也得不到任何益處。
They are just going to talk, talk, talk, talk, talk, which is a dead thing, which becomes a dead in your mind  nothing but conditioning takes place.
他們只會不斷地說、說、說、說、說，這毫無意義，最終只會變成你頭腦中的死物，除了制約之外，什麼也得不到。
By reading books, you are not going to achieve it either.
透過閱讀書籍，你也無法達成它。
Books are dead: you read the books you accumulate more dead on your left hand side.
書籍是僵死的：你閱讀書籍，只會讓左脈累積更多死物。
By the Right side, you do the thing by accumulating the Left Side.
而右脈，則是透過累積左脈的死物來發揮作用。
But you use also the Left Side for your Right side.
但同時你也會用左脈來理解你的右脈。
Because, you see, if you have read a book, then, so, “Yes, yes, yes! You see!
因為，你看，如果你讀過一本書，那麼，所以，「是的，是的，是的！你看！
Now Mataji is not that person, you see,
現在瑪塔吉不是那個人，你看，
because there was in this book this was written and how Mataji explains that?”
因為這本書裡寫了這個，而瑪塔吉如何解釋的？」
So all the time you are playing with these two knots within you Rajoguna and Tamoguna:
所以你始終在與內在的這兩種結糾纏——右脈和左脈
these two knots are within you and that’s why your attention is not on the Spirit.
這兩種結存在於你之內，正因如此，你的注意力不在靈上。
Third is the Sattvoguna, you can call it: the one by which we try to know God;
第三種是中脈，你可以稱之為：我們藉此試圖認識神；
is the one by which we try to see things that, “No, this is not all right!”
是我們藉此試圖看清事物，並意識到：「不，這並不妥當！」
“We give up this and give up that and we should take to Rajoguna.”
我們放棄這個，放棄那個，我們應該走向右脈。
We should give up Rajoguna and we should take to Sattvoguna:
我們應該放棄右脈，我們應該走向中脈：
is the central path, where we try to say, “We must be God. But what can we do to be God?”
這是中道:人們試圖說：「我們必須成為神。但我們能做什麼來成為神呢？」
Like I have told you, people think that by meditating...
就像我告訴過你們的，人們認為透過冥想可以做到。……
You see some people have told me
有些人曾告訴我
“Oh, I have been meditating Mother for the last twenty-five years!”
「哦母親，我已經冥想二十五年了！」
“Now,” I said, “what have you been meditating?”
「那麼，」我說，「你一直在冥想什麼？」
I mean, there have been people I have known who have been ‘meditating’. But where, and how?
我的意思是，我認識一些人一直在『冥想』。但究竟在何處，又是如何冥想的呢？
It’s funny, you know, how people can do it.
你知道嗎，這真的很有趣，人們竟然能做到這種事。
We had neighbours there, and somebody had given them a mantra
我們在那裡有鄰居，有人給了他們一句口訣
and he was a man, a very big man, I should say,
而他是一位男士，應該說，是個非常了不起的人物，
he was really governor of the Reserve Bank of India!
他可是印度儲備銀行的總裁呢！
And they would get up four o’clock till six o’clock,
他們會從凌晨四點起床直到六點，
they were meditating and saying some sort of a mantra, absolutely rumble tumble,
他們在冥想並念誦某種口訣，轟隆隆地念個不停，
and they were doing it and doing it and doing it till it was about twenty years you see!
他們就這樣一直做、一直做、一直做，持續了大約二十年，你明白嗎！
Till they absolutely became dilapidated, their hands became like this, feet became like this and swollen bodies and all that, and then they died.
直到他們徹底病入膏肓，雙手變成這樣，雙腳變成這樣，身體腫脹等等，然後就死了。
Till then they were going on and on until the end! And even when they were laid down in bed they could not move on, still they were on with it!
他們就這樣一直持續到最後！即使躺在床上也無法動彈，卻依然堅持著！
They had become completely dead. You won’t believe how they had become. I wish I had shown you their photographs.
他們已經完全麻木。你無法想像他們變成了什麼樣子。真希望我能給你看他們的照片。
Absolutely bedridden,
完全臥床不起，
and their bodies were swollen up and they could not even move their legs
身體腫脹，連腿都無法移動。
and food was given to them and somebody used to take them out and do everything.
有人會給他們食物，也會有人帶他們出去，為他們處理一切事務。
I mean, they couldn’t move any part of their body, they were all deadened and finished, like that, and still they were saying the mantras!
我的意思是，他們身體的任何部位都無法動彈，全都麻木癱瘓，就像那樣，但他們仍在念誦口訣！
I said, “Now when are you going to get the fruit of all these mantras?”
我問：「那麼，你們什麼時候才能得到這些口訣的果報呢？」
They said, “You see our mother…” They have a mother,
他們說：「你看我們的母親……」他們有一位母親，
and their mother has promised that, “When you will die you will get it.”
他們的母親曾承諾：「等你死了就會得到它。」
They died and nothing happened!
他們死了，卻什麼也沒發生！
The body was so heavy nobody could lift it, and it was a big problem.
屍體沉重到無人能抬起，這成了大問題。
So they were deadening themselves, all the time they were deadening and deadening!
於是他們不斷地麻痺自己，持續地麻痺再麻痺！
Instead of going towards life, they were deadening themselves only.
他們非但沒有走向生命，反而在自我麻痺。
Now, you see, I could not tell them anything
你看，我什麼也勸不動他們，
because they were not very willing to listen to me.
因為他們不太願意聽我說。
They had become so much addicted to that habit of saying mantra,
他們已經對念口訣上了癮，
that even doctors could not do anything about it,
就連醫生也束手無策，
nobody could do, they would not take any medicine, they were just doing mantras only.
誰都無能為力，他們不願服用任何藥物，只顧念誦口訣。
Their mouth was saying mantra and the whole body was stiff like that!
他們口中念著口訣，全身卻僵硬如石！
And they died and people said, “What great people have died, you know!
他們就這樣死去，人們卻說：「你知道嗎，多麼偉大的人就這樣離世了！」
We must take their darshanas they have died.”
我們必須瞻仰他們，他們已經過世了。」
Now, you start looking at them and you say, “Now, what to do?”
現在，你開始看著他們，然後說：「現在，該怎麼辦呢？」
And the people they came and they said, “Oh, great people have died!
人們前來並說道：「噢，偉大的人們已經過世了！
Then they took the name of God till the end!”
於是他們一直呼喚神的名號直到最後！」
And then you blame God:
然後你責怪上帝：
“Why, you see, why is that they took the name of God and why did they die like that?”
「你看，為什麼他們取了上帝的名字，卻那樣死去？」
I mean you must see where you are hitting your head!
我的意思是，你必須看清自己撞到頭的地方在哪裡！
Supposing that is the door and if you go on hitting your head here
假設那是門，如果你繼續在這裡撞頭
and then you say, “Mother we hit our head for twenty years why didn’t you find the way?”
然後你說：「母親，我們撞了二十年頭，為什麼你沒找到路？」
I mean this is not the way! The way is there. That’s the way you have to get it.
我的意思是這不是路！路就在那裡。你必須找到那條路。
If this is not the way, why are you hitting there?
如果這路不對，你為什麼還在那裡撞頭？
This is because of the Rajoguna problems,
這是因為右脈的問題，
the Rajoguna problem that we can do something about it.
我們可以對右脈問題做些什麼。
People just cannot believe that you cannot do anything about it,
人們就是無法相信你對此無能為力，
because in a very, very subtle way Mr. E-G-O is present!
因為在非常、非常隱密的方式中，自我先生無所不在！
You say anything to them immediately it comes up like a snake, I have seen it.
你對他們說任何話，它立刻就會像蛇一樣竄出來，我親眼見過。
“Oh, Mataji said that! No, I can’t bear it! Why did she say that?”
「噢，瑪塔吉竟然這麼說！不，我無法接受！她為什麼要那樣說？」
I mean, why did I say, means I see things and that’s why I am saying! You will also come on this side one day and you will start seeing.
我的意思是，我之所以會說，是因為我親眼見證了這些事，所以才這麼說！總有一天你也會來到這裡，屆時你將親眼目睹。
And what I say is absolute truth or not you can verify it!
至於我所說的是否是絕對的真理，你可以親自驗證！
But why should I say, is the main point!
但重點是，我為什麼要說這些呢！
I don’t want to disturb you.
我不想打擾你。
I have brought you here and I have called you here to give you something special.
我帶你來這裡，並召喚你前來，是為了給你一份特別的東西。
All right now if that is so, let us have a compact of it,
好吧，既然如此，讓我們就此達成一個約定，
some sort of a compact deal about it,
某種關於此事的約定協議。
that I give you something and then you receive it and the compact,
我給予你某些東西，然後你接收它，這份約定，
the whole thing, should work in you, and then you decide about it.
這整個過程，應該在你心中運作，然後由你來決定。
Instead of that if one word you say,
而不是如果你說了一個字，
immediately the snake comes, “Oh! She said this to us, let’s walk out!”
那條（自我）的毒蛇就會立刻跳出來，「哦！她對我們說了這個，我們走吧！」
Now what should I say? “You are all right”?
那我該說什麼呢？「你們都沒問題」？
“You need not seek. You are perfect”? Is that the way should I pamper your ego?
「你們無需追尋，你們已是完美」？難道我該這樣縱容你們的自我嗎？
No, it should not be so.
不，不該如此。
Neither do I condemn anybody. I do not say that,
我也不譴責任何人。我不會那樣說，
“It is because you are like this ,you are condemned!” — no!
「正因你如此，你才被定罪！」——不！
But you must see the Reality,
但你必須看見實相，
that you are not there as yet, the Reality has not come to you,
你尚未抵達那裏，實相尚未降臨於你，
you must see the Reality as a whole.
你必須將實相視為一個整體。
For example, I am a Mother and you are hitting your head here.
舉例來說，我身為一位母親，而你正在這裡撞頭。
Now if I tell you, “My child for heaven’s sake don’t hit your head,
現在如果我告訴你：「我的孩子，看在老天的份上別再撞頭了，
you will break your head. Go there, there’s the door.”
你會撞破頭的。去那邊，門在那裡。」
Then you say, “I’m on my own, who are you to tell me?”
然後你說：「我自己做主，你憑什麼管我？」
Now this is a bit too much for a Mother to bear.
這對一位母親來說實在有點難以承受。
Now she says, “Please see, this is the door you get out of this door.”
現在她說：「請看，這扇門就是你從這裡出去的門。」
That’s why you need a Mother, you don’t need anybody else.
這就是為什麼你需要一位母親，你不需要其他任何人。
Because anybody else would just say, “Oh, all right,
因為其他任何人都只會說：「哦，好吧，」
you go ahead! Break your head and finished with everything!
你儘管去吧！撞碎你的頭，一切都結束了！
Good riddance of the bad rubbish!” But a Mother is not like that.
「真是謝天謝地，擺脫這個壞東西真是太好了！」但一位母親不會這樣想。
She thinks about it, she thinks, “Oh, my children are there,
她思考著，她想著：「噢，我的孩子們在那裡，
they are seeking, they are seekers. I have to go on telling them and telling them,
他們正在尋找，他們是求道者。我必須繼續告訴他們，不斷地告訴他們。
so that at least they open themselves.”
這樣至少他們會敞開心扉。」
But they’ll go on hitting their heads,
但他們會繼續撞得頭破血流，
whatever you may try, you see unless and until this wisdom comes into the head.
無論你如何嘗試，他們都會繼續碰壁，除非他們真正領悟到這種智慧。
And it’s such a vicious circle, I tell you.
我告訴你，這真是個惡性循環。
The wisdom cannot come till this lowest granthi breaks,
智慧無法降臨，直到這最低層的結被解開，
the lowest knot breaks, where a person starts understanding one simple point:
當最低層的結被解開，一個人便開始理解一個簡單的道理：
that human beings cannot do it.
人做不到，
God has to do it.
神才能做到。
So the surrendering starts.
於是，臣服開始了。
God has to do it. You cannot do it. Only thing we have to say, “Oh, Lord please!” that’s all.
這必須由神來完成。你無法做到。我們唯一要說的就是：「噢，主啊，求祢！」如此而已。
You have to just knock at the door.
你只需要敲門。
You don’t have to argue out whether Christ was correct or not, whether Buddha was correct or not — don’t discuss any dogmas.
你不需要爭論基督是否正確，佛陀是否正確——不要討論任何教條。
All these people, all those who are supposed to be in charge of religions, have created nothing but useless dogmas to quarrel and fight!
所有這些人，所有那些被認為掌管宗教的人，除了製造無用的教條來爭吵和鬥爭之外，什麼也沒做！
And I was amazed to see these people when they have their meetings:
而當我看到這些人開會時，我感到驚訝：
“We have to discuss who is going to be elected for this
「我們必須討論誰將被選為這個職位，
and what is going to be the agenda for the budget of this thing,
以及這個項目的預算議程將會是什麼。」
and then lastly what will be the menu for the next year?”
那麼最後，明年的菜單會是什麼呢？
That’s all they do! I mean if that is God’s job, I am quite surprised and you should be.
這就是他們所做的一切！我的意思是，如果這就是神的工作，我相當驚訝，你也應該感到驚訝。
I mean is this the way these people are going to bring Reality within you by bringing you all kinds of unreal and useless things?
我的意思是，這些人難道就是透過帶給你各種不真實且無用的東西，來將實相帶入你內在嗎？
And they are doing it, and we are in it all the time, we are in it.
而他們正在這麼做，而我們始終置身其中，我們深陷其中。
We are identified with it, because.....
我們與之認同，因為……
BREAK IN RECORDING
錄音中斷
...this yellow stuff, you see, absolutely.
……這黃色的東西，你看，絕對是。
It gives you also. To me, it gives me nauseous, a feeling of...
它也會讓你。對我來說，它讓我感到噁心，一種……的感覺。
Most of these people, egoistical, have bad liver
這些人大多自私自利，肝臟狀況不佳
and also they have, they get this trouble of migraine.
而且他們還患有偏頭痛的困擾
And also they get all liver problems
同時他們也出現各種肝臟問題
and this yellow colour especially is expressing their liver temperaments.
這種黃色尤其反映出他們肝氣鬱結的體質
Then on top of that, they think, “What’s wrong in doing anything?”
除此之外，他們還認為：「做任何事有什麼不對？」
Already we are on one side then, “What’s wrong?” then starts, then we start drinking,
我們本來就已經偏一邊了，然後「有什麼不對？」就開始了，接著他們開始喝酒，
because we must deny all that is good.
因為必須否定所有美好的事物。
Now let me tell you one thing:
現在讓我告訴你一件事：
whatever things people do which are egoistical, the things that they do that destroys them.
人們所做的任何出於自私自利的事情，那些最終會摧毀他們的行為。
You see, it’s sort of a thing they want to destroy themselves. Perhaps in a subtle way their ego wants to destroy itself.
你看，某種程度來說，是他們想要毀滅自我。
It is such a thing that they work it out in such a sub-human way.
正是這樣的事情，他們處理這件事的方式如此不人性。
For example, for a person like me, I cannot understand a man who goes to a pub
舉例來說，像我這樣的人，無法理解一個會去酒吧的人
and sees another person coming in and falling down all over:
然後看到另一個人走進來，跌得四腳朝天：
you see such a man coming out then how do you enter in?
你看到這樣的人走出來，那你又怎麼會想進去呢？
It’s like a lunatic asylum!
簡直就像瘋人院一樣！
I mean if you go to lunatic asylum and you see a lunatic coming out, .
我的意思是，如果你去瘋人院，看到一個瘋子走出來，。
then you would not like to go inside
那麼你就不會想進去
But this, I can’t understand how human beings do. They see.
但這個，我無法理解人類是怎麼做到的。他們看見。
Now you know it very well that nobody so far has been even honoured because he’s a drunkard.
現在你很清楚，到目前為止，沒有人僅僅因為他是個酒鬼而受到尊敬。
Has there been anybody in the whole world?
整個世界上有這樣的人嗎？
While the whole world drinks, but is there anybody honoured?
當全世界都在飲酒，但有人因此受到尊崇嗎？
In the history I would like to know: was anybody honoured?
在歷史中我想知道：有人因此受到尊崇嗎？
Any man who has deceived his wife and has married ten women has been honoured for that? Is there anybody honoured?
任何欺騙妻子並娶了十個女人的男人，會因此受到尊崇嗎？有人因此受到尊崇嗎？
I mean they say that many geniuses, I call them geniasses, are like that.
我的意思是，他們說許多天才，我稱他們為「天才混蛋」，就是這樣。
You see, maybe they are just like the radiograms from where some music is coming,
你看，也許他們就像那些傳出音樂的收音機，
but it doesn’t do anything inside it.
但他們內部其實什麼也沒做。
And they, if they become your models,
而他們，如果成為你的榜樣，
you might be becoming geniasses yourself, without even any genius in you.
你可能會變成天才傻瓜，即使你本身沒有任何天賦。
So all funny models we set up but do we ever erect their statues?
所以我們樹立了這麼多滑稽的榜樣，但我們是否曾為它們豎立雕像？
Do we garland them? Do we worship them? Why?
我們是否為它們戴上花環？我們是否崇拜它們？為什麼？
Anybody may say against Christ,
任何人都可以反對基督，
I don’t say that anybody can stop you, I mean because you are on your own.
我並不是說因為你“孤身一人”，就沒有人能阻止你。
You see, on your own trip is one of the worst trips that I could think of.
你看，這種「孤身一人」的旅程是我能想到的最糟糕的旅程之一。
What have you found so far to be on your own? Nothing! You haven’t found your own properties.
到目前為止，你發現獨自一人有什麼好處嗎？什麼都沒有！你還沒找到屬於自己的特質。
You haven’t found out your own nature. You have not found out the beauty that you are.
你還沒發掘自己的本性，也沒發現自己擁有的美好。
What are you all with? Will you go out anywhere without taking any money with you?
你到底在幹嘛？你會不帶錢就出門嗎？
You don’t even have a ticket!
你連一張票都沒有！
So just it’s a joke, that you are on your own. You are not!
所以這只是個玩笑，說你是獨自一人。你並不是！
You are not, because your own is missing,
你並不是，因為你自己的本性不見了，
is missing, it’s not there. We have to find out that own.
不見了，它不在那裡。我們必須找出那個本質。
Our attention should be on that own.
我們的注意力應該放在它身上。
And why, why do we always indulge into these three complications all the time.
而為何，為何我們總是沉溺於這三種複雜的結之中。
Like even in the centre, is about Sattvoguna.
即使在核心層面，也是關於中脈
Because we feel many people do feel: that’s also a very modern blessing,
因為我們覺得許多人確實感受到：那也是一種非常現代的祝福。
I would say, that everyone feels the need to seek.
我會說，每個人都感受到尋求的需求。
But when you see how Joan of Arc was punished
但是當你看到聖女貞德如何被懲罰時
and how things happened in the past,
以及過去的種種事件，
how people were mad and dogmatic and egoistical in the name of religion:
人們以宗教之名瘋狂、教條且自我為中心：
you don’t know what to do. You see the funny people!
你會不知所措。你看到了那些可笑的人們！
Then you get all these horrible gurus coming here
接著，各種可怕的「大師」紛紛來到這裡
and taking from you and doing all kinds of things.
騙取你的錢財，並做各種各樣的事情。
You think, “What’s all going on?”
你會想：「這到底是怎麼回事？」
Then you see people giving you sermons and lectures and all their private life:
然後你看到人們對你講道、說教，還有他們所有的私生活：
nothing in them bubbling, nothing so special, nothing so sweet about them.
他們身上沒有任何靈性，沒有什麼特別之處，也沒有什麼令人愉悅的地方
Then you feel, “What is this going on?”
然後你會想：「這到底是怎麼回事？」
And that is the central path where you are really seeking
而這正是你真正尋求的核心道路。
and then you say, “No, let me do it myself!” I can assure you, you cannot,
然後你說：「不，讓我自己來！」我可以向你保證，你做不到的，
it’s not meant to be.
這真可笑，
Why?
為什麼？
I mean if somebody says, “All right you come to my house. Just come down and you’ll get it.”
我的意思是，如果有人說：「好吧，你來我家。來你就能明白。」
Then why do you want to do it still? What is the reason?
你為什麼還要繼續找呢？理由是什麼？
There are many people who have been here
這裡有許多人
who don’t like when I tell them, “Please give up this mantra of yours.
不喜歡我告訴他們：「請放棄你的這個口訣。
It’s not going to do any good to you!”
這對你沒有任何好處！」
They say, “Why Mataji?” As if they become the mantra!
他們說：「為什麼是瑪塔吉？」好像他們自己就是口訣似的！
And the mantra itself is “Rumble tumble”! Nobody knows a word about Sanskrit!
而口訣本身卻是「隆隆作響」！沒人懂半句梵文！
Nobody knows a word about what it means, where to take which mantra. There is no living process behind it — nothing!
沒人知道口訣的意義何在，該在哪裡使用哪個口訣。它背後沒有任何生命力——什麼都沒有！
I am shocked at it sometimes.
有時候我對此感到震驚。
Sometimes I feel, instead of water you are taking poison
有時我覺得，你喝下的不是水而是毒藥
And when you tell about the Reality
當我談論實相
and you tell them, “This is how it works out, and it has to work out within you.
並告訴他們：「事情就是這樣運作的，而且必須在你內在運作。
It is an internal working. It is an internal yoga
這是一種內在的運作。這是一種內在的瑜伽
which has to work out, which you have to feel it yourself; you have to see yourself
這必須要實踐出來，你必須自己去感受；你必須審視自己
and you have to see it in others, and you have to work it out.” People don’t like it.
並且你必須在他人身上看見，你必須去實踐它。」人們並不喜歡聽這個。
This is also because of the third misidentification you have of your Sattvoguna.
這也是因為你對自身中脈的第三種誤解(結)。
Because artificiality starts from the very beginning,
因為虛偽從一開始就存在，
the artificiality goes on and on, till even you come to Sattvoguna which is the seeking
這種人為造作持續不斷，直到你甚至最終抵中脈，那是一種追尋
In seeking also there’s artificiality.
在追尋之中，也同樣存在著人為造作。
Now if I may tell you that I can see you through and through:
現在，若我告訴你，我能將你看得透徹：
it’s a fact. I can.
這是事實。我確實能夠。
Now you put up a show before me, whatever show you want, but I can see it.
現在你在我面前表演，不管你想表演什麼，我都看得出來。
But I do not show that,
但我不表現出來，
I don’t want to show, it’s all right.
我不想表現，沒關係。
Sometimes I am very unhappy when I see some people; I know there’s a big problem about them.
我看到一些人會非常難過；我知道他們有很大的問題。
You haven’t got that experience, but supposing when you become a Sahaj Yogi you will feel it.
你還沒有那種經驗，但假設當你成為一個霎哈嘉瑜珈士時你會感覺到。
Those who have got it can feel it. You will feel so concerned about things.
那些已經獲得這種體驗的人都能感受到。你會對很多事情感到無比關心。
And sometimes you feel very elated to see some people
有時候，看到有些人狀態很好，
are in a very good shape and some are in a very elated shape.
有些人狀況很好，你會感到非常欣慰。
I can see you through and through. I can see everything.
我能看透你的一切。我能看到一切。
But still my love, you see,
但我的愛如此深沉，
is such that it doesn’t allow me to see those things that will recede my attention.
使我無法看見那些會分散我注意力的事物。
I can see my love working it out:
我能看到我的愛在努力釐清這一切：
It tries to build it and make it. I have to work it out.
它試圖建構並創造出來。我必須努力
But then my attention is a very special stuff: it goes to a great extent.
但我的注意力是非常特殊的東西：它會延伸到很大的程度。
Now the love and the attention play a part.
現在，愛和注意力都扮演著重要的角色
In my case, you see, my love is in my heart, it’s my Left Side. This one is not.
在我的情況，你看，我的愛在我的心中，那是我的左脈。而這個（指注意力）則不在那裡。
It plays hand in hand with the attention.
它與注意力相輔相成。
Now attention is in the centre and my Sahaja Yoga is on the right hand side.
現在注意力在中心，而我的霎哈嘉瑜珈則位於右脈。
So the attention is also very stubborn:
所以注意力也非常固執：
it plays, to a point, it goes up to a point,
它會努力，在某種程度上，它會上升到某個程度，
then it recedes back, again, it goes down and says, “All right, forget it!
然後它又退回去，再次下沉，說：「好吧，算了！
You just can’t do it, not yet.”
你就是做不到，還不行。」
Because, you see, love can also spoil, so they balance.
因為，你看，愛也會溺愛，所以它們需要保持平衡。
Like in a driving you have an accelerator and a brake.
就像開車時有油門和煞車。
You can put an accelerator to a point
你可以把油門踩到某個程度
but if it goes beyond a point then it might spoil the whole show, so you have to put it down.
但如果超過了一個程度，那就可能破壞整件事，所以你得踩煞車。
It has to keep in relation with the whole programme, with all the people around.
它必須與整個場景、與周圍所有人保持協調。
Now say if there’s a person who comes here,
現在假設有個人來到這裡，
who is a very troublesome fellow, he has very bad vibrations, he drinks and he troubles us,
他是個很麻煩的傢伙，帶著很不好的生命能量，他喝酒並且惹事生非，
and he just comes here to disturb us; he argues.
他只是來打擾我們；他還愛爭論。
One day I tolerate him,
我容忍他一次，
second time I tolerate, third time he doesn’t turn up, he just doesn’t turn up!
第二次我還容忍，第三次他沒來，他就是不來了！
People don’t know how he doesn’t come, “Oh, he was transferred.”
大家不知道他怎麼不來，「哦，他被調走了。」
I didn’t do that but it happens.
我沒做甚麼，但這情況確實會發生。
The attention just recedes:
注意力就這樣減退：
no importance to such a person; he is useless, because what he can achieve?
對這種人沒什麼意義；他沒用，因為他能成就什麼呢？
Thousands and millions can be given it just like this.
成千上萬的人可以輕易得到同樣的東西。
Why should God worry about people who are not interested in their own well-being?
上帝為什麼要擔心那些對自己福祉不感興趣的人？
He’s not going to fall at their feet. He can create the whole universe; I mean,
祂不會向他們俯首稱臣。祂可以創造整個宇宙；我的意思是，
He can create all other types of human beings.
祂可以創造所有其他類型的人類。
So this is also there, this attention, you see:
所以這個也存在，你看到的這種注意力：
it’s a very proud stuff.
這是一種非常自豪的東西。
It has its own protocol and these protocols are divided into these seven centres.
它有自己的法則，這些法則被劃分到這七個中心。
And any one of these Deities, specially Christ, the Lord as you call Him,
而這些任何一位神祇，尤其是基督，正如你們稱祂為的主，
He is really the Lord you know, not an easy person, if He gets angry, it’s impossible.
祂確實是真正的主，不是個好惹的人，如果祂生氣了，那就不可能（輕易應對）。
He loves you; no doubt, but to a point.
他愛你；毫無疑問，但有個限度。
He loves me much more than He loves you.
他對我的愛遠勝於對你的愛。
If He finds that there is a problem for me He will have nothing to do with you.
如果祂發現你為我製造了麻煩，祂就不會理會你。
As long as you are receiving it, and behaving yourself, all right.
只要你在接受，並且舉止得當，就沒問題。
Same about Mahavira, same about Buddha:
對摩訶毘羅（Mahavira）也是一樣，對佛陀也一樣：
we are on one side. So they all support, they all help,
我們都站在同一邊。所以他們都支持，都幫忙，
and all of them are absolutely in unison and in complete understanding; nobody fights them.
而且他們完全一致、完全理解；沒有人與他們對抗。
It’s a complete integration.
這是完全的整合。
Only I am the person in between,
只有我，是中間那個
trying to say, “All right, just for a little bit, let’s have it this way and that way.
試著說：「好吧，就暫時這樣，或那樣。」
Let’s do it, you see.” Like a chairman sitting on the chair and telling them,
「就照這樣做，你看。」就像一位主席坐在椅子上對他們說，
“All right. It’s all right now. Please forgive! Please forgive me now!”
「好了。現在沒事了。請原諒他們！請原諒！」
But somehow (unclear).
但不知怎的（不清楚）。
It happens.
事情還是發生了。
Then for a Sahaja Yogi it is essential to know there are certain rules
因此對於一個霎哈嘉瑜珈士來說，了解霎哈嘉瑜珈的某些規則
and regulations of Sahaj Yoga.
了解霎哈嘉瑜珈的某些規則和戒律至關重要。
Immediately your vibrations are less to begin with.
你的生命能量馬上就減弱了，起初就是如此。
I don’t do anything.
不是我做的。
People say, “Mother you have taken away my vibrations!”
人們說：「母親，你取消了我的生命能量！」
I say, “Why should I? I am so anxious to give it away! I mean I am fed up of it!”
我說：「我為什麼要這樣做？我多想把它給你們！我是說，我有太多了！」
I would love to give everything, all this to you.
我願意把一切、所有這些都給你。
But if there’s something wrong with you what am I to do?
但如果你本身有問題，我能怎麼辦？
Now supposing you put a lid
現在假設你把一個蓋子
on top of a pitcher and put it in the Ganges
蓋在一個水罐上，然後把它放進恆河裡
and you say, “No! Ganges is flowing, now what am I to do?”
你會說：「不！恆河正在流動，現在我該怎麼辦？」
Remove the lid!
把蓋子拿掉！
And it is very subtle, very subtle.
而且非常微妙，非常精微。
You don’t realise how subtle it is,
你無法察覺它有多精微
only in vibrations: “Oh God! I’ve lost my vibrations!” That’s all!
只有透過生命能量:「哦天啊！我的生命能量沒了！」就這樣！
So vibrations are the most important things for Sahaja Yogis.
所以，生命能量對霎哈嘉瑜珈士來說是最重要的
The most important thing is to achieve a complete state of vibrations,
最重要的是達到完整的生命能量狀態，
when your Realisation is completely integrated,
當你的自覺完全整合，
your physical being, your emotional being, your Spiritual being is complete, in unison, there’s a complete balance within you.
你的身體、情緒、靈都是完整的、和諧一致的，你內在有一種完全的平衡。
Then only the vibrations flow and that’s why antar-yoga is important.
只有那時生命能量才能流動，這就是內在瑜珈（antar-yoga）如此重要的原因。
It is not only lecturing that is going to help you. Of course,
光靠講授是不夠的，當然，
there are vibrations in it and they work out:
講課中也包含生命能量，它們確實有效：
I try through my vibrations of my words, I try to disentangle you.
我嘗試透過我話語的生命能量來幫助你脫結。
But that is to a point, where you have to yourself take up and work it out,
但那只到某個程度，你得親自接受並處理它，
the antar-yoga, the inner yoga,
透過靜坐、冥想以及霎哈嘉瑜珈所建議的各種練習，來實踐內在瑜珈（antar-yoga），
and do various things that Sahaj Yoga has suggested.
透過靜坐、冥想以及霎哈嘉瑜珈所建議的各種練習，來實踐內在瑜珈（antar-yoga）。
Now I have, you know that, my grandchildren are realised-souls and
現在我有，你知道的，我的孫兒孫女們都是自覺靈，而且
they’re very high quality realised-souls
而且是程度很高的自覺靈，
and they understand a lot about Kundalini from very childhood.
從很小的時候就能理解很多關於昆達里尼的事。
Yesterday one of the girls was feeling the Left Nabhi very much,
昨天其中一個女孩感受到了左臍輪（Left Nabhi）非常強烈，
all over, and she said, “Now I will know how to remove it.”
她全身都感覺到了，她說：「現在我就知道怎麼把它除掉了。」
And she brought pieces of paper and she tied them round her there.
然後她拿了幾張紙，把它們綁在她那裡。
Then she took vibrations like that.
然後她用這種方式吸收生命能量。
So she said that, “Now they are all passing into this paper!” You see.
她說：「現在它們都轉移到這張紙上！」
Actually while doing that,
實際上，她在做這件事的時候，
she was giving bandhan to it.
她正對它施予束縛（bandhan）。
She was moving her own vibrations around it, she was binding them.
她把自己的生命能量引導到紙上，把它們綁起來。
And then she took them and she said, “Alright, put them in the fire,” and they burned it.
然後她拿起紙，說：「好吧，放進火裡，」他們就把紙燒掉。
And her tension was reduced. And everywhere, everybody felt better.
她的緊張感減輕了。每個地方、每個人都感覺好多了。
It’s so fantastic it is!
真的非常棒！
And now this girl is seven
現在這個女孩已經七歲了
but I have a granddaughter, she’s hardly two, and she’s very great too.
但我有一個孫女，才剛滿兩歲，她也非常了不起。
She just comes on to the point. She says, “This is the problem!”
她總是直截了當地指出重點。她說：「這就是問題！」
And I have a grandson who just climbs on somebody and he clears them out.
我還有一個孫子，他爬到別人身上，然後把他們的負能量都釋放出來。
His vibrations are clear, people have seen it.
他的能量很清晰，大家都親眼見過。
And there are many children like that, who are born in this country.
在這個國家出生的孩子有很多都是這樣的。
How are you going to understand it?
你打算怎麼去理解？
Only by attending to some sort of a meditation course or something like that?
只有參加某種形式的禪修課程或類似的東西才能理解嗎？
Paying for it? No, you have to be lively people.
付錢去學？不，你們必須成為有活力的人。
Sahaja Yogis should realise one thing:
霎哈嘉瑜珈士應該意識到一件事：
that they are the foundation of the new world.
他們是新世界的基礎。
This is a very, very big responsibility.
這是一個非常非常重大的責任。
And the foundations have to be very solid.
而這些基礎必須非常穩固。
They are made out of stones, no doubt,
毫無疑問，它們是由石頭構成的，
but they have to be really solid, absolutely solid, because they are in the foundation.
但它們必須真正堅固，絕對堅固，因為它們地基的一部分。
They are chiselled out much more.
它們被鑿得更多。
They are to be cleared out much more.
它們需要被清理得更多。
But if the foundation is not good
但如果地基不好
we cannot build the complete edifice, you cannot do anything about it.
我們無法建起完整的建築，而對此我們無能為力。
First, the foundation is important, and that’s why it’s nice we are getting a few people.
首先，地基很重要，這就是為什麼我們很高興能吸引一些人。
But it’s taking a bit too much time, I think, the foundation itself.
但我認為，這基礎本身花的時間有點太多了。
Every stone has to look after oneself,
每一塊石頭都必須照顧好自己，
and has to work it out in a much deeper way
並且必須以更深的方式去處理，
and work out the vibrations and must evolve the methods,
整理出那些生命能量，並且必須發展所有的方法，
all the methods, by which your depth is created.
透過這些方法來創造你們的深度。
Nothing is important but this: that every one of you should be real solid people.
沒有其他事比這更重要：你們每一個人都應該成為真正穩健的人。
In the end, I will just tell you that the subtle part of these chakras, is how to understand them.
最後，我只想告訴你們，這些脈輪微妙之處在於如何理解它們。
The first side, the first entanglement with the jada-prakruti as you call it,
首先，也就是與你們所說的物質（jada-prakruti）的第一個結，
the matter, is to know the auspiciousness,
物質，是要知道吉祥之處，
auspiciousness of things: what is auspicious, what is not auspicious.
事物的吉祥：什麼是吉祥，什麼是不吉祥。
If you understand the auspiciousness
如果你理解吉祥之意
then you will understand that you can overcome the binding of the matter.
那你就會明白你可以超越物質的結。
Now, even auspiciousness can become quite maddening to people.
然而，即使吉祥也可能讓人變得相當瘋狂。
I have seen it. I have seen people washing their hands fifty-five times,
我見過這樣的例子。我見過有人洗手五十五次，
pulling their hair hundred times. That’s not the way.
抓頭髮一百次。那不是正確的方式。
But you must understand what is auspicious, what is not auspicious.
但你必須了解何者是吉利，何者是不吉利。
For example,
例如，
we can say,
我們可以說，
how we sit in a programme is not important so much.
我們在活動中的坐姿並不那麼重要。
You may be little bit sometimes pushing back, pushing forward, may be sitting any way:
你有時可能會稍微往後靠、往前傾，或是以任何方式坐著：
that’s not important.
那並不重要。
But the auspiciousness of sitting is that: have you reverence in your mind when you are sitting?
但端坐的吉祥之處在於：你端坐時心中是否有崇敬之心？
There should be a reverence in you.
你內心應該懷有一份恭敬。
When you are sitting for your meditation,
當你坐下來冥想時，
are you taking upon yourself that, “Oh, I am going to achieve it today."
你是否對自己說：「喔，我今天要成就它。」
or out of reverence you are sitting in a surrendering mood, in a surrendering position?
或者出於崇敬，以一種臣服的心態和姿勢坐著？
The reverence part is very important, once you start understanding reverence.
一旦你開始理解崇敬，就會發現崇敬非常重要。
I have seen people putting both their legs towards me,
我見過有人把雙腿朝向我放，
sitting down like that. I have seen people with very arrogant ways of sitting.
那樣坐著。我也見過有人坐姿非常傲慢。
For example, sitting like this, you see,
例如，像這樣坐，你看，
before anybody who is supposed to be revered: you should not sit like this.
在任何理應受到尊敬的人面前：你不應該這樣坐。 ...
If you sit like this then there is no reverence.
如果你這樣坐，那就沒有崇敬之心。 ...
This is you sit when you are in the authority yourself!
當你自己成為權威時，你就該這樣坐！ ...
You should sit with your both legs like this and sit in reverence.
你應該像這樣雙腿盤坐，懷著敬意而坐。 ...
Now this pose is not important.
現在這個姿勢並不重要。 ...
You can be absolutely burning with ego within you and could be sitting like this.
你內心可以充滿自我，但你也可以這樣坐著。
So I’m again telling you: auspiciousness is what is within you,
所以我再告訴你：吉祥是存在於你內在的，
what you think about it, what is happening to you:
你如何看待它，在於你的感覺：
Are you feeling reverence within you? Are you feeling the reverence by your pose?
你是否在內心感到虔敬？你是否透過你的姿勢感受到那份虔敬？
This is your own judgment. This is your decision.
這是你自己的判斷。這是你的決定。
This is nothing to do with how you should sit, whether you sit on your one leg or two legs,
這與你應該如何坐無關，無論你是盤著一條腿還是兩條腿坐著，
it’s not the most important thing,
這並不是最重要的，
but do you feel that, by this you are relaxed and you are in a reverence position?
但你是否感覺到，藉由這樣你放鬆了並處於一種恭敬的姿態？
This is the thing. If you feel you are in a reverence position, that’s all right.
這就是重點。如果你覺得自己處於恭敬的姿態，那就很好。
That is what you have to do, is to understand auspiciousness.
你要做的，是要理解吉祥的意義。
An example I will tell you, of auspiciousness:
我將告訴你一個關於吉祥的例子：
for example, now, you are a wife in a family,
例如，現在你是一個家庭中的妻子，
you are a husband in a family.
你是一個家庭中的丈夫。
Now how you treat your wife? Do you treat her like a goddess of the family?
那麼你現在如何對待你的妻子？你是否把她當作家庭的女神來對待？
Do you?
是嗎？
Do you treat your husband as a man who brings God in the family?
你是否把你的丈夫當作一個把神帶入家庭的人來對待？
You see, this auspiciousness is the way, how you feel about, is the auspiciousness.
你看，這種吉祥就是方式，你對它的感受，就是那吉祥。
How you feel about a chair? You sit on the chair; say for example,
你對一張椅子的感受是什麼？你坐在椅子上；舉例來說，
now how do you feel about the chair? Do you feel it’s a chair because it’s very expensive?
現在你對這張椅子的感受如何？你覺得它是椅子，是因為它非常昂貴嗎？
Because it is your own? Or because somebody has given you?
因為是你自己的？還是因為有人送給你？
The reverence is there, about the chair, that, “No, it is the chair which was occupied by my mother
對那把椅子有一種崇敬，譬如說：「不，那是我母親坐過的椅子，
so it is to be revered, or by my father, so it is to be revered,
所以應該被尊崇，或者是我父親坐過的，所以應該被尊崇，
or it is just a chair which is handled just for utility
或者它只是一把僅用於實用的椅子，
or you have just got it for a some sort of a deviant thing?
或者你只是因為某種不正當的目的才得到它？
Wherever you sit, now, say for meditation: you are sitting in a place.
無論你坐在哪裡，現在，比方說冥想：你就是坐在一個地方。
I have seen people doing all kinds of funny things, in the name of meditation.
我見過人們以「冥想」之名做各種滑稽的事。
For example, they’ll be smoking first, you see.
例如，你會看到他們先抽菸。
Now what are you going to do? The smoke, the what do you call the.....
那你要怎麼辦呢？菸味，還有你怎麼稱呼那個……
ashtray would be just there
煙灰缸就放在那裡
and then they would put their feet like this, “Now let us do the meditation!”
然後他們會把腳這樣擺好，「現在我們來冥想！」
This aspect is very much missing here because
這一面在這裡非常缺失，因為
people have lost all that. I think they had it very much there, but it is lost.
人們已經完全失去了崇敬。我想他們曾經有，但現在已經失去了。
And auspiciousness is a very, very sort of a thing
而吉祥是一種非常、精微的東西
which gradually, when you train yourself, you’ll understand.
當你逐漸訓練自己時，你會理解的。
And by auspiciousness you will understand the value of matter.
而透過吉祥，你會理解物質的價值。
You will not value the matter then, but the auspiciousness of it.
那時你不再看重物質本身，而是看重它所蘊含的吉祥意義。
To you, the important thing will be say a hair from the head of Mohammed Prophet.
對你來說，最重要的事或許是先知穆罕默德的一根頭髮。
It’s much more auspicious than all the world put together.
那比整個世界萬物加起來都要吉祥得多。
I went to Kashmir as I told you,
正如我告訴你的，我去了克什米爾，
and we were just crossing through and I asked the driver, I said, “What’s this place?”
我們當時路過，我問了司機，我說：「這是什麼地方？」
He said, “Why?” I said. “Is there any temple here?
他說：「怎麼了？」我說：「這裡有廟嗎？
What is this place? It’s so beautiful?”
這是什麼地方？好美啊？」
So my husband looked around, he said, “What’s beautiful about it? I don’t understand.
於是我丈夫環顧四周，他說：「哪裡美？我不懂。
There’s nothing here, around?”
這裡什麼都沒有，周圍？」
He said, “No, there is nothing. But there’s a place just there, you can see that,
他說：「沒有，什麼都沒有。但就在那邊有個地方，你可以看到，」
where the hair of Mohammed Prophet is kept.”
穆罕默德先知的頭髮被保存在哪裡。」
I said, “That’s it!”
我說：「就是這個！」
No joy, beauty, I could ever get it from anywhere from any place.
我無法從任何地方、任何場所獲得真正的喜悅和美好。
It could be very beautiful, you may feel that, “This is the heaven here!” .
它可能非常美麗，你可能會覺得：「這裡就是天堂！」
For me it may not be there.
對我而言，它可能並非如此。
It may be that place where one hair of Mohammed Prophet is sitting.
它或許是穆罕默德先知的一根頭髮靜靜佇立的地方──
It’s auspicious.
這是吉祥的。
Auspiciousness is judged through vibrations.
吉祥與否是透過生命能量來判斷。
So you cannot say, “How are you to judge the auspiciousness?”
所以你無法說：「你如何判斷吉祥？」
Through your vibrations you can. So use your vibratory awareness for auspiciousness.
透過你的生命能量，你就能判斷。因此，運用你的生命能量去感知吉祥吧。
That’s how you can look after your Left Side,
這就是你照顧左脈的方式，
which I have told you in a very short way.
這是我以非常簡短的方式告訴你的。
For that you don’t have to read books
為此你無需閱讀書籍
and you don’t have to say, “How many times, Mother, I should wash my hands?
也無需詢問：「母親，我該洗手多少次？
How many times I should give this bandhan and all that?”
我該進行多少次班丹儀式之類的？」
It’s only when you get your vibrations the best, that’s the most auspicious time.
唯有當你感受到最佳生命能量時，那才是最吉祥的時刻。
Keep it at that point, because again into the rituals
就保持在那個點上，因為在進行各種儀式時，
you’ll go, “Hold it with your left hand and hold it with your right hand,”
你會說：「用左手拿著它，用右手拿著它。」
and all going wrong. And then some, “Oh, Mother I did the wrong way!” Then what is it?
結果全都搞錯了。然後有人會說：「噢，母親，我做錯了！」那又怎樣呢？
That’s not the way!
那不是正確的方式！
The thing is, the essence of it,
事情是這樣的，其本質在於，
if you get your vibrations all right, that’s what is to be auspicious.
如果你能調整好自身的生命能量，那便是吉祥的時刻。
Maybe when you are sitting down you are not getting your vibrations,
也許你坐著的時候感覺不到生命能量，
you think that maybe might go something wrong with it:
你會想是不是哪裡出了問題：
is it I am not revered properly? Let me have the vibrations.
是不是我沒有做到應有的崇敬？讓我感受到生命能量吧。
Why, what’s the matter?
怎麼了，有什麼問題嗎？
Why is it that I am not feeling the vibrations well?
為什麼我感覺不到生命能量？
That’s how it should be. You can judge it through your vibrations
本來就該如此。你可以透過你的生命能量來判斷。
Now auspiciousness is very important for Sahaja Yogis
現在，吉祥對霎哈嘉瑜伽士來說非常重要
because all that they do should be auspicious.
因為他們所做的一切都應該是吉祥的。
Whatever is inauspicious you shouldn’t do.
任何不吉祥的事情你都不應該做。
Now you will be surprised, sometimes you might think
現在你會感到驚訝，有時你可能會想
that say going to a particular place is very important.
前往某個特定地點非常重要。
But maybe you will find that you have lost your purse
但或許你會發現自己遺失了錢包
or you cannot go there or may be that somehow or the other that the road is blocked,
或是無法前往該處，又或者道路不知為何被封鎖了，
you have to go by another way.
你必須改走另一條路。
Accept it!
接受這一切！
Maybe that is auspicious.
也許這才是吉祥的。
Maybe that you have to go that way.
或許你必須走那條路。
Maybe there is somebody who is waiting for you there,
或許那裡有人在等著你。
you have to give your vibrations to that place, there is some need there
你必須將你的生命能量傳遞到那個地方，那裡存在著某種需求。
because you are an instrument of auspiciousness.
因為你是吉祥的工具。
You have to spread the auspiciousness.
你必須散播這份吉祥。
And what is auspiciousness? Is nothing but the blessings of God.
而什麼是吉祥？無非就是神的祝福。
To feel the blessings of God.
感受神的祝福。
He blesses you all the time.
祂時時刻刻都在祝福你。
His hand is all the time on your hand, He looks after you.
祂的手始終牽著你的手，祂看顧著你。
When you seek auspiciousness you seek His hand.
當你尋求吉祥時，你就是在尋求祂的手。
You are always under His hand.
你永遠都在祂的庇護之下。
He’s your shepherd. You are all the time under His guidance.
祂是你的牧者。你時刻都在祂的引領之中。
That is what auspiciousness is, in the real sense.
這才是真正意義上的吉祥。
To feel it, all angels around you.
去感受它，你身邊所有的天使。
Everybody is there to help. Everybody is trying to bring you to Reality:
每個人都樂於伸出援手。每個人都試圖引領你走向真理：
that is the auspiciousness.
這便是吉祥。
Once you start doing it gradually you will find the joy of living will pour into you,
當你逐步實踐，便會發現生命的喜悅將湧入心間，
the joy of God’s blessings will pour into you, when you will feel His hands.
當你感受到祂的雙手時，神的祝福之喜亦將傾注於你。
It is not important that you become a very successful person in life.
人生中成為一個非常成功的人並不重要。
I have seen such successful people in life, so-called successful:
我見過這樣所謂成功的人：
so unhappy, so miserable, so terrible and so boring and so troublesome.
如此不快樂、如此悲慘、如此可怕、如此無聊又如此麻煩。
They are good for nothing! People say, “Oh! He has died, it’s a good thing!”
他們一無是處！人們會說：「噢！他死了，真是件好事！」
They have done no good to anybody, nobody bothers about them.
他們對任何人都沒有益處，也沒有人在乎他們。
When they are in position people look after them,
當他們在位時，人們會照顧他們，
once they are gone nobody even bothers about them.
一旦他們離開，就沒人再想起他們了。
Auspiciousness gives you the right idea of Divine importance,
吉祥給予你對神聖重要性的正確理解。
means where the Divinity flows behind you
意指神性在你身後流動
and goes around you and takes you around and gives you the complete joy:
環繞著你，帶領你，賜予你完全的喜悅：
the movement of the wind.
如同地心引力的流動。
It’s a beautiful thing to be auspicious.
能擁有祥瑞是件美好的事。
It takes you away from inauspiciousness when you ask for auspiciousness.
當你祈求吉祥時，它會帶你遠離不祥。
But do not make a ritual out of it,
但不要將它變成儀式，
which I want to tell you hundred and hundred and one times
這點我想告訴你千百次
that do not make a ritual of anything
不要將任何事情變成儀式。
because you deaden it, like all other people have done it.
因為你使它麻木了，就像其他所有人都做過的那樣。
I hope after my death you people do not do all this.
我希望在我死後，你們這些人不會做這一切。
Because then it becomes a superstition.
因為那樣它就變成了一種迷信。
Auspiciousness should never be confused with superstition.
吉祥永遠不應與迷信混淆。
Because people were not that alert
因為人們不夠警覺
and not so subtle they could not make out what is ugliness,
且不夠細膩，無法分辨何為醜陋，
that is superstition, and what is beauty, that is auspiciousness.
那便是迷信，何為美麗，那便是吉祥。
They made all mistakes and they committed all these crimes
他們犯下所有錯誤，也犯下所有這些罪行
But you people be careful, because you are subtle people.
但你們要小心，因為你們是精微的人。
Do not make it a superstitious thing,
不要讓它變成迷信的事，
but an auspicious thing.
而是吉祥的事。
When you speak, it should be auspicious.
當你們說話時，應當是吉祥的。
I have seen many people have a habit of speaking very inauspicious things,
我見過許多人有種習慣，總愛說些非常不吉利的話，
especially with the left Vishuddhi – very inauspicious.
尤其是左脈喉輪——極其不祥。
Like you invite somebody to your house for a dinner party.
就像你邀請某人來家裡參加晚宴，
And he says, “Oh! I saw such a crowd coming in I felt that there was a fire on!”
他卻說：「哎呀！我看到這麼多人湧進來，還以為是失火了呢！」
And what a thing to say! He thinks he has been smart,
這說的是什麼話！他以為自己很聰明，
a very smart man to say such a thing.
一個非常聰明的人才會說出這樣的話。
Or he’ll utter a very dirty joke at the time when there’s a wedding going on.
或者他會在婚禮進行時說一個非常低俗的笑話。
There are many people.
現場有很多人。
The inauspiciousness can form such a satanic force.
不祥之氣能形成如此邪惡的力量。
Most of the tantrism has come out of inauspicious people.
多數密宗修行者皆出自不祥之人。
Do you know this, that tantrism is nothing but inauspicious mastery?
你可知曉，密教不過是不祥之術的掌控？
Before the Deity, before the Gods,
在神祇面前，在眾神之前，
if you do something extremely inauspicious,
如果你做了極度不祥之事，
you make the attention of the Gods and all its protection to get out of it
就會讓眾神的關注與所有庇護都離你而去，
and then you do all satanic things there. This is the basis of all these tantrikas.
然後你便會在那裡行盡一切邪魔之事。這就是所有密宗修行者的根本。
What is hell? Is nothing but inauspicious living.
地獄是什麼？不過就是不祥的生活罷了。
Because the attention of this God is not on you, the blessings are not there.
正因神的關注不在你身上，祝福也就不會降臨。
Then you will understand that vibrations teach you auspiciousness.
屆時你便會明白，生命能量正教導你何謂吉祥。
You think of somebody and you get stinging, “Oh God!
一想到某人，心頭就一陣刺痛：「天啊！」
What a man he is!” You may think he is a very big man
「這樣的人！」你可能會覺得他是個非常了不起的人
immediately you say, “Oh, he is inauspicious. We have nothing to do with him.”
你立刻便說：「哎，這人不吉利。我們不要與他有任何瓜葛。」
Sahaja Yogis should not aspire for the worldly success and worldly things,
霎哈嘉瑜伽士不應追求世俗的成功與世俗的事物，
but for auspicious things, so that they get the blessings of God.
而應追求吉祥之事，以得神的祝福。
Because those who have got also all kinds of worldly things
因為那些已經擁有各種世俗事物的人
are the most wretched souls ever living and are a curse to this Mother Earth.
他們是史上最可悲的靈魂，更是這片大地之母的詛咒。
She is fed up with them. They are sinful.
她對他們已經受夠了。他們罪孽深重。
I do not want to tell you, if people behave in this manner,
我不想告訴你，如果人們這樣做，
where they will go and what will happen,
他們將去往何處，又會發生什麼事，
because that’s too much for me to say at this juncture.
因為在這個時候，這對我來說實在是太多了。
But that is what it is
但事實就是如此
about, I would say, your great poet, say Blake, has talked about it and told about it.
關於這一點，我想說，像布萊克這樣的偉大詩人，曾談論過並闡述過這一點。
The Hell, he has described.
他所描述的，正是地獄。
So many of them have described, I do not want to elaborate on it.
既然已經有這麼多人描述過地獄，我就不再贅述了。
The other side is the Right side, how to get out of the second side of it.
另一邊是右脈，如何從右脈脫身？
What is the subtle point of the Right side?
右脈的關鍵是什麼？
Is discipline.
就是紀律。
You see, first you have to say, England was a very disciplined country,
首先要說明的是，英國曾是一個紀律嚴明的國家，
over disciplined, artificially disciplined,
過度自律、人為地自律、
militarily regimented type.
軍隊式管理類型。
I do not mean that discipline at all.
我指的絕不是那種紀律。
The discipline which is in you.  It comes automatically.
你內在的自律。它會自然而然地流露出來。
Not regimentation! Again the confusion should not be there,
不是那種刻板的規章制度！這點不該再有誤解，
because I want to make it extremely clear.
因為我想把這一點說得非常清楚。
It’s very easy to confuse things because of these knots.
因為我們內裡的這些結很容易讓人產生誤解。
So, when I say that you must have discipline,
所以，當我說你必須有紀律時，
is an inner discipline, absolute inner.
是一種內在的修養，絕對的內在自律。
You don’t have to do anything about it, but it is built in,
你無需刻意去做任何事，它自然而然地融入你的生命，
because you start enjoying that discipline within you.
因為你開始享受內心那份自律。
Discipline is, in Sanskrit language, we can call it as sadachar
在梵文中，紀律可稱為「sadachar」
is ‘good behaviour,’ actually, if you translate it.
其實，如果翻譯過來，就是「良好行為」。
But is much more than that,
但這遠不止於此，
is much more sadachar is much more.
遠不止於此。 「好的行為」遠不止於此。
It is a discipline: what time we get up in the morning?
這是一項紀律：我們早上幾點起床？
How do we greet the morning?
我們該如何迎接早晨？
The sun has risen.
太陽升起了。
“What’s wrong in getting up at ten o’clock?”
「十點鐘起床有什麼不對嗎？」
“Nothing wrong my child,
「這沒什麼錯，孩子，
but you are losing the beauty of the morning.”
「但你正錯過早晨的美好。」
Morning time is the time when the sun is coming, the rays are coming.
清晨是太陽升起、陽光灑落的時刻。
That is the special time when the sun throws its real rays of Divinity.
那正是太陽灑下真正神聖光芒的特殊時刻。
Actually the Right side is the sun side,
其實右脈是太陽脈，
and it starts with your rising in the morning, very much.
這一切都始於你早晨起床的那一刻，確實如此。
But not the hatha yogi style where you become bony people,
但不是那種會讓人變得骨瘦如柴的哈達瑜珈風格，
where you fast for three hundred days
在那裡你將禁食三百天
and then three hundred days you go on shouting at people
然後你又對人們大吼大叫了三百天
and three hundred days you start cursing them.
到了第三百天，你便開始咒罵他們。
I do not mean that.
我不是那個意思。
By discipline I mean that a certain amount of respect for yourself.
我所說的「紀律」，是指對自己抱持某種程度的尊重。
It is a respect. As there is auspiciousness,
這是一種敬意。正因有吉祥之兆，
this is a respect of your own being because it is ego.
這是對你自身存在的尊重，這是一種尊重。正如吉祥之意，
How much you respect your ego, Let me see?
你有多尊重自己的自我？讓我看看？
Assert your ego is different from respecting your ahambhav, your dignity.
主張自我與尊重你的「尊嚴」（ahambhav）是兩回事。
Your position in life, how much do you respect?
你對自己的人生地位，有多重視？
Do you sell it for money?
你會為了金錢出賣它嗎？
Do you sell it for a chair?
你會為了椅子出賣它嗎？
Do you sell it for any positions in life?
你會為了生活中的任何地位出賣它嗎？
A kind of a discipline within yourself:
這是一種內在的自律。
not to jabber too much,
既不能喋喋不休，
not to talk less. But that doesn’t mean that you try the balancing of it
更也不能過度沉默寡言。但這並不代表你要試著在兩者之間取得平衡
it’s something innately built in which can work out through Sahaja Yoga
這是與生俱來的特質，可透過霎哈嘉瑜珈來解決
if you see your vibrations, again.
如果你再次由你的生命能量來評斷。
You have to be respectable.
你必須自尊自愛。
In the first one, you have to respect, and in the second one, you have to be respectable.
第一種情況下，你必須尊重他人；第二種情況下，你必須讓自己值得被尊重。
Respect yourself.
尊重自己。
People think that, supposing they don’t bathe their body
有些人覺得，就算幾個月不洗澡，
for months together, “What’s wrong?” Nothing wrong.
「有什麼問題嗎？」 沒什麼問題。
If you do not respect yourself, nature is not going to respect you
如果你不尊重自己，大自然也不會尊重你
Physically you should respect, mentally, emotionally.
在身體上，你應該予以尊重；在精神上、情感上亦然。
If say you like to see pornographic photos
假設你喜歡看色情照片
you have no respect for yourself.
你完全不尊重自己。
If you want to eat filth, you have no respect for yourself.
如果你想吃髒東西，那你就是不尊重自己。
You want to waste your eyes, you want to waste your attention with this.
你根本看不起自己。你想浪費你的眼睛，你想浪費你的注意力。
You shouldn’t like anything that is absurd, useless, frivolous.
你不該喜歡任何荒謬、無用、輕浮的事物。
You shouldn’t charge your chakras with something nonsensical and filthy.
你不該用那些荒謬又骯髒的東西來充滿你的輪穴。
When you start respecting yourself you will really know how to respect others.
當你開始尊重自己時，你才會真正懂得如何尊重他人。
Those who cannot respect themselves cannot respect others.
無法尊重自己的人，也無法尊重他人。
And respect that is good in others.
並尊重他人身上的美好之處。
And do not worry about their faults but respect them for their good
不要糾結於他們的缺點，而要尊重他們身上的優點
so that you also have good in you and you respect yourself.
這樣你內心也會充滿美好，並能尊重自己。
That is not asserting, this respect is never asserting,
這不是在強勢，這種尊重從來都不是在強勢，
it’s very comforting,
它令人感到安心，
extremely comforting. A person who respects himself is the most congenial person to live with.
令人倍感安心。一個尊重自己的人，是最令人愉悅的相處對象。
He doesn’t come forward too much,
他不會過度張揚，
neither he recedes back too much.
也不會過度退縮。
He’s just there.
他就在那裡。
Like a wise man,
就像一位智者，
you know he’s there: you can always approach such a person.
你知道他在那裡：你隨時都可以找這樣的人談談。
He doesn’t do anything outwardly.
他表面上什麼也沒做。
He doesn’t try to show off.
他不會刻意炫耀。
He doesn’t try to create a sort of an aura about him.
他並不會刻意營造某種氣場。
He’s not boasting about himself.
他並非在自吹自擂。
Ego can be easily handled
自我其實很容易控制，
if you respect yourself.
如果你尊重自己。
Then you will not feel hurt.
這樣你就不會感到受傷。
Because who can be insulting but yourself to yourself?
畢竟，除了自己之外，誰又能侮辱自己呢？
Supposing there are some
假設有幾個
dogs barking at an elephant,
幾隻狗對著一頭大象吠叫，
he just, “Swish, swish,” he goes on like that. Have you seen an elephant? Very interesting.
他只是「唰、唰」地這樣動著。你看過大象嗎？非常有趣。
He walks and his majestic way.
他邁步前行，姿態威嚴。
And he finds some dog barking he just, “Swish, swish!” Very nicely he does.
他聽到有狗在吠叫，便「唰、唰！」地揮了揮手，然後繼續它那威嚴的步伐。
He puts them like that, you see. Like a little child whistling at that
你看，它就是這樣對待它們的，就像小孩吹著口哨
and goes on its own majestic way. He says, “Oh you doggy! It’s all right, come along.”
便繼續沿著它那氣勢恢宏的道路前行。他說：「哎呀，你這小狗！沒關係，跟我來吧。」
He is not bothered as to how they treat him.
他不在乎他們如何對待他。
They bark at him and he just walks, in his dignity.
他們對他吠叫，而他只是昂首闊步，氣度不凡。
That’s why we say that an elephant is a very dignified animal.
這就是為什麼我們說大象是一種非常莊嚴的動物。
It walks with its dignity.
它步履間盡顯尊嚴。
A person like that doesn’t take to cheap fashions and cheap things:
像這樣的人是不會喜歡廉價的時尚和廉價物品的：
he is in his own dignity.
他展現出應有的尊嚴。
He does not try to adjust himself to the norms of things that they have created.
他不會試圖讓自己去迎合別人設定的標準。
You cannot play into the hands of these bogus people,
你不能落入那些虛偽之人的圈套，
who say that your weight should be, I don’t know how much,
那些說你的體重應該是多少的人，我不知道具體是多少，
and your this thing should be so much. All the women trying to do that.
你的這個面向應該達到多少。所有女人都在試圖這麼做。
Tomorrow they may come and say your hair should be so long.
明天他們可能會來告訴你，你的頭髮應該留這麼長。
So you become like this, so all the women trying to do that.
所以你變得像這樣，於是所有女人都想效仿。
You must wear wigs, so everybody is trying to wear wigs.
既然必須戴假髮，所以大家都爭相戴假髮。
You don’t play into their hands anymore once you start respecting yourself.
一旦你開始尊重自己，就不會再落入他們的圈套了。
Like in India, they started a fashion of sleeves you see.
就像在印度一樣，他們掀起了一股袖子的風潮，你看。
They started first from here, so much sleeves.
一開始非常流行，袖子特別多。
Then they said, “So much sleeves, so much sleeves,” then some said, “So much sleeves!”
接著他們說：「好多的袖子，好多的袖子」，然後有些人說：「袖子太多了！」
Then some said, “So much sleeves!” You see, it goes on.
接著有人說：「袖子也太多了吧！」你看，這風潮沒完沒了。
So somebody asked me, “What about you?”
於是有人問我：「那你呢？」
I said, “I had them from my, the very beginning,
我說：「我從一開始就穿袖子，
and I am going to have them that way only, because it’s too much to run this race. I cannot!”
「而且我以後也只會穿袖子，因為要跟這些花里胡哨的東西較勁太累了。我根本忙不過來！」
Because I have a tailor who does this job, now, I have no time to waste for all this nonsense,
因為我有位裁縫師專門負責這項工作，所以現在我沒時間浪費在這些無謂的事情上，
and why? What is the need?
而且，有什麼必要？
Whatever has been found out traditionally is accepted.
只要是傳統上認可的，就應該被接受。
And you will find all these fashions drop out just like that!
你會發現，這些流行趨勢轉眼間就會消失無蹤！
Now, in our saris also, we have fashions come up.
如今，我們的紗麗也出現了各種新潮流。
You see, there was a fashion of sari where they wanted to have a mini saris.
你知道嗎，當時有一股風潮，大家都想穿迷你紗麗。
You see, whatever fashions you have they want to have the fashion!
你看，無論你追隨什麼潮流，他們都想跟上這股潮流！
And you don’t know about this? It’s very interesting.
（笑聲）你不知道嗎？這很有意思。
They used to have mini saris. So mini saris could be only up to this point.
以前有迷你紗麗。所以迷你紗麗的長度最多只能到這裡。
And they started going up, up to this point, you know.
然後他們長度開始往上延伸，一直爬到這個地方，你知道的。
Some people tried to do it on all them,
有些人嘗試把所有紗麗都做成迷你款，
and then they gave up, they said, “It’s nothing doing! It doesn’t look nice, you see.”
然後他們就放棄了，說：「這行不通！你看，這樣看起來不太好看。」
And it was started by a company because they wanted to sell more yarn, you see.
這一切都是由一家公司發起的，迷你紗麗的出現是因為一家公司想賣更多紗線。你明白的。
By mini saris they could sell more yarn and charge the same for a sari because half-sari
透過迷你紗麗，他們能銷售更多紗線，同時對一件紗麗收取相同的費用，因為半件紗麗
and you sell it as a mini. It’s only mini, and money is double!
卻以迷你版出售。它只是迷你尺寸，但利潤卻是雙倍！
So they tried it! But it failed in India, so the sari remains the same.
於是他們嘗試了！但在印度失敗了，所以紗麗依然保持原樣。
Then they started printing only the front part of the saris, this is a new fashion, then another.
接著他們開始只印製紗麗的前半部分，這是一種新時尚，然後又出現了另一種。
I said, “Nothing doing! You better buy one traditional sari which lasts you all your life!”
我說：「別想了！你還是買一條傳統紗麗吧，那可是能穿一輩子的！」
You can sort it out. All these things fall off, you see.
你可以處理好的。你看，這些東西都會過時的，
Like in Victorian times they must have worked out many things
就像維多利亞時代那樣，他們當時肯定已經想通了很多事情
it falls off. Then something falls off.
有些東西會過時，然後有些東西又會過時。
Something traditional that is there may not be useful today
有些傳統的東西現在可能沒用了，
but something eternally traditional will be there all your life. That is really traditional.
但有些永恆的傳統將伴隨你一生。那才是真正的傳統。
Whichever falls off, which goes off, people find it useless, it is no good, then throw it out.
不管什麼東西過時了，人們覺得沒用了，覺得沒用了，於是就把它扔掉。
Now many things that you are doing, for example nowadays
現在你正在做許多事情，例如最近
people are putting those pins inside the cheeks.
人們正將那些別針塞進臉頰內側。
Now, they are putting them I have seen them: putting them in nose there,
現在，他們正把別針放進去——我親眼見過：把別針放進鼻子裡，
putting a pin here; putting a pin here.
這裡別一根針；那裡別一根針。
This all will go away! After some time you will find them putting something in their hair.
這一切都會消失！過一陣子，你會發現他們開始往頭髮裡別東西了。
Let them do it. They are foolish people.
就讓他們去吧。他們是些愚蠢的人。
But this is nothing. They can do something in a very subtle manner, you see.
但這算不了什麼。你看，他們能以極其隱晦的方式行事。
Like the Elizabethan collar you had.
就像你之前戴的那個伊莉莎白項圈一樣。
Because Queen Elizabeth had some problem in the back here, so they started Elizabethan collar.
由於伊莉莎白女王的背部這裡有些問題，所以他們開始使用伊莉莎白項圈。
So everybody started wearing an Elizabethan collar.
於是大家開始戴起伊莉莎白頸圈。
Then, at the time of Victoria, she had some sort of a problem at the back here.
後來，在維多利亞時期，她這裡的後背似乎出了點問題。
So, she started a thing. Everybody started wearing it. Why?
於是，她開創了一股風潮。大家都開始穿了。為什麼呢？
You have your attire, dress, your sitting position.
你的穿著、衣著，以及坐姿。
Your thinking itself is not fashioned by others,
你的思考本身並非由他人塑造，
it is only fashioned through your vibratory awareness.
它只應由你自身的生命能量感知來塑造。
Immediately if you read a book,
假設你讀一本書，
you come on to the point and you say, “Oh! This is not true,
你直截了當地說：「喔！這本書裡這個說法不對，
but it is this what is true in this!”
「但這本書裡這個說法是對的！」
Immediately you start scanning the books:
你立刻開始翻閱那些書：
you know which is the true book, which is not the true book.
你知道哪本書是真理，哪本書不是。
You just don’t read nonsense, because you know it’s all falsehood,
你根本不會去讀那些胡言亂語，因為你知道那全是謊言，
it’s all story telling.
都是編造的故事。
You do not want to read something nonsensical.
你肯定不想讀一些胡言亂語。
So you just understand the sense and the nonsense of it. So it works out.
所以你能夠理解其中的真諦和謬誤。這樣就行了。
And that’s how, when you start respecting yourself,
正因如此，當你開始尊重自己時，
respecting your thoughts,
尊重自己的想法，
respecting your inspirations,
敬重自己的靈感，
your dreams,
你的夢想，
your aspirations, your visions,
你的抱負、你的願景，
write them down. Whatever thought you get, write it down.
寫下來。無論想到什麼，都寫下來。
Whatever inspiration you get, write it down.
無論你獲得什麼靈感，都把它寫下來。
Whatever visions you think you should have for yourself, write it down.
無論你認為自己應該擁有什麼樣的願景，都把它寫下來。
All that you think that should be the future, write it down, and pray for it.
凡是你認為應該成為未來的，都寫下來，並為此祈禱。
The greatest quality on this one is when you respect yourself.
最重要的特質就是尊重自己。
When you respect yourself, you are respected.
當你尊重自己時，你也會受到尊重。
By whom? By the Gods,
誰會尊重你呢？神，
by the Divine Force, by all the angels,
藉著神聖之力，藉著眾天使，
and whatever you want to do, will be done.
無論你想做什麼，都會實現。
Then it comes, “Thy will be done!”
然後，你會聽到「願祢的旨意成就！」
But that will has to come out of respect for yourself.
但這種旨意必須源自於對自身的尊重。
If it is coming out of some other considerations,
如果這是基於其他考量，
for example, now in Bombay they want to have an ashram.
例如，現在孟買的人們希望蓋靜修中心。
People have all funny ideas about ashrams.
人們對蓋靜修中心總是有種種奇思怪想。
They want to have an ashram:
他們想建立一個靜修中心：
why having this ashram? Some people are very clever, I know all of them.
為什麼要建立這個靜修中心？有些人非常聰明，我全都認識他們。
And they think they can make some money out of it.
而且他們還以為能從中賺點錢。
Foolish things as they are.
儘管這想法很愚蠢。
Then some of them think that by staying there,
於是，其中有些人認為，只要留在那裡，
“We can pass our old age very nicely,
「我們可以過得很安穩，
it will be a cheap thing, because Mataji is not going to charge anything extra,
這會是很便宜的，因為瑪塔吉不會額外收費，
so it will be a nice cheap thing. Let’s buy that.”
「所以這會是個既好又便宜的東西。我們就買這個吧。」
Some of them are thinking, “It’s a very good place where,
其中有些人心想：「這真是個好地方，
in young age we can go there and, it will be a good idea, we can run away from work.
趁我們還年輕的時候去那裡吧，這會是個好主意，我們可以暫時逃離工作。
We’ll stay in the ashram and after all Sahaja Yoga won’t be that hard work you see.
我們會住在靜修中心，畢竟霎哈嘉瑜伽也沒那麼辛苦，你明白。
So it will be nice living there.”
「所以住在那裡應該很不錯。」
All these considerations, when they are in the minds of the people
當這些考量都縈繞在人們心中時
you will never get your ashram done, take it from me.
你永遠都建不成你的靜修中心，相信我。
“We’ll sleep till ten o’clock, who is going to wake us up?”
「我們要睡到十點，誰能怎樣？」
“We’ll do whatever we like in the ashram. We’ll use it for our own purposes,”
「我們會在靜修中心裡為所欲為。我們會把它用在自己的目的上，」
“We will not do any meditation. We will not do anything, whatsoever!”
「我們不會做任何冥想。我們什麼都不做，絕對什麼都不做！」
“We’ll do no work at all. We’ll not help anything in the organising of Sahaja Yoga
「我們完全不會做任何工作。在薩哈賈瑜伽的組織工作中，我們不參與霎哈嘉瑜伽的組織工作。」
or an organising people, we will not bring them.”
也不組織任何人，我們不會帶他們來。」
After all what will happen?
說到底，會發生什麼事呢？
You’ll lose your vibrations.
你會失去你的生命能量。
If you respect yourself,
如果你尊重自己，
the expression of your Self must be respected.
那麼你表達”我”的方式也必須被尊重。
Tell your body to behave itself,
告訴你的身體要安分點，
tell your mind to behave itself,
告訴你的心要安分點，
and tell your emotions to behave itself.
並告訴你的情緒要安分一點。
I have seen people hankering after a girlfriend or a boyfriend
我見過有人渴望交到女朋友或男朋友
and asking for this and asking for that.
這要求那要求。
And then coming to me and telling, “Mother, what can I do about this girlfriend or a boyfriend?”
然後跑來對我說：「母親，我該怎麼處理這個女朋友或男朋友呢？」
or some sort of a thing like that.
或者類似那樣的事。
All these things are not going to help you.
這些事情都對你沒有幫助。
You have to respect yourself. You are an entity by yourself.
你必須尊重自己。你本身就是一個獨立的個體。
You are not going to bow down to anyone.
你不需向任何人低頭。
You are not going to accept anything.
你是不會接受
You are not going to accept anything that is not respectable for you.
你不會接受任何對你而言不值得尊重的事
And this is how you are going to manage your Right Side.
這就是你管理自身右脈的方式。
Now the centre part is very important in your seeking.
現在，在你求道的過程，中脈至關重要。
In your seeking
在求道的過程，
you have to know that you are seeking your Spirit.
你必須明白，你正在尋求你的靈。
You are seeking that your attention should now pour through your Spirit.
你正尋求讓你的注意力此刻透過你的靈傾注而出。
You are not seeking the Spirit but you are going to become one with the Spirit.
你並非在尋求靈，而是將與靈合而為一。
That is your seeking is.
這就是你求道的真諦。
For that, it is very important to know about your own chakras.
因此，了解自己的輪穴非常重要。
You must know how they are caught up and face up to it.
你必須知道它們是如何運作的，正視它。
You must face the truth there.
你必須在那裡面對真相。
You have to be absolutely honest and truthful about it.
你必須對此絕對誠實坦率
That’s the point in the centre.
這就是中脈。
If you are honest, the centre point will work out.
只要你誠實，中脈就會發揮作用。
For example, I’ll tell you: I cured a gentleman who was suffering from, say, cancer.
舉個例子來說，我告訴你：我曾治癒一位患有，譬如說，癌症的先生。
I cured him, all right. He has gone away.
我確實治好了他。沒錯。他後來離開了。
He didn’t even write a letter of thanks.
他甚至連一封感謝信都沒寫。
And if anybody asks him he says, “Oh no, still I am waiting.”
如果有人問他，他會說：「哦，不，我還在等。」
Four years have passed, three years have passed and still "I am waiting for it."
四年過去了，三年過去了，我卻依然「在等待」。
I don’t know.” He was to die in three month’s time!
「我不知道。」他原本只剩三個月的生命！
He has been dishonest to God.
他對上帝不誠實。
He should have told people, “No, Mother has cured me!”
他本該告訴大家：「不，是母親治好了我！」
Then he gets back his cancer.
然後他的癌症復發了。
And then he blames God for that.
然後他竟把這歸咎於上帝。
So truth must be accepted.
因此，必須接受真相。
You have to be truthful and honest for the central path,
你必須誠實正直地走在中脈，就必須真誠且正直，
absolute on the truth.
絕對地信奉真理。
“Yes, this is the truth we have found out, we have felt the vibrations.”
「是的，這就是我們所發現的真相，我們感受到生命能量。」
“We are not feeling the vibrations,”
「我們感受不到生命能量，」
or there is some mixture.
或者有複雜的情況。
“Yes, I am catching on this.” There are many people say, “No Mother, I’m not catching!”
「是的，我的輪穴有感染。」有很多人會說：「不，不，母親，我的輪穴沒有感染！」我知道他們怎麼了。他們在撒謊。你們在對誰說謊呢？